二次大战迫近
With the coming of the Second World War...
很多被困在欧洲的人们 怀着希望甚至急切地
...many eyes in imprisoned Europe turned hopefully, or desperately...
想要来到自由的美洲
...toward the freedom of the Americas.
里斯本成为热络的航运地点
Lisbon became the great embarkation point.
不过并非每个人均能直接 到达里斯本
But not everybody could get to Lisbon directly.
因此一条艰苦迂回的 逃难路线出现
And so a torturous, roundabout refugee trail sprang up.
从巴黎到马赛
Paris to Marseilles...
越过地中海到奥朗
...across the Mediterranean to Oran.
然后搭火车、汽车或走路 沿着非洲的海岸线
Then, by train or auto or foot, across the rim of Africa...
来到法属摩洛哥的卡萨布兰卡
...to Casablanca in French Morocco.
在这里幸运的人 藉着钱、影响力、或运气
Here, the fortunate ones, through money or influence or luck...
可能拿到出境许可证 然后赶往里斯本
...might obtain exit visas and scurry to Lisbon.
再从里斯本到新世界
And from Lisbon to the New World.
不过其余的人则在卡萨布兰卡
But the others wait in Casablanca.
等待、等待、再等待
And wait and wait
所有军官注意
To all officers:
两位身怀重要官方文件的德国快递员
Two German couriers carrying official documents...
在从奥朗开出的火车上被杀
...murdered on train from Oran.
凶手和可能的共犯 正前往卡萨布兰卡
Murderer and possible accomplices headed for Casablanca.
拘留所有嫌疑人物 并搜查被偷走的文件
Round up all suspicious characters and search them for stolen document.
这个任务相当重要
Important.
(法语)
可否看一下你的证件?
May we see your papers?
我没有带在身上
I don't think I have them on me.
既然如此 我们必须请你跟我们走 等一下 可能是...
- In that case, you'll have to come along. - Wait. It 's possible that I...
在这里
Yes. Here they are.
这些证件三个星期前已过期了  你必须跟我们走
These papers expired three weeks ago. You'll have to come along.
站住!
Halt!
“自由，平等，同胞爱”
那边发生什么事?  我不知道  亲爱的
- What on earth is going on there? - I don't know, my dear.
对不起  先生  你没听说吗?
Pardon, monsieur. Pardon, madame. Have you not heard?
我们听到的不多 我们听得明白的更少
We hear very little, and we understand even less.
两位德国快递员在沙漠被发现遭谋杀  那无人的沙漠
Two German couriers were found murdered in the desert. The unoccupied desert.
这是惯例的搜捕自由主义者
This is the customary roundup of refugees, liberals...
难民和给警察首长的漂亮女孩
...and, of course, a beautiful young girl for Renault, the prefect of police.
不幸的是伴随着这些不快乐的难民
Along with these unappy refugees,
是欧洲的坏蛋们 都集中到卡萨布兰卡
the scum of Europe has gravitated to Casablanca.
有些为了出境证等了好几年
Some of them have been waiting years for a visa.
我请求你  先生  自己要当心 谨慎提防
I beg of you, monsieur, watch yourself. Be on guard.
这地方布满贪婪的人
This place is full of vultures.
到处都是贪婪的人  到处都是
Vultures everywhere. Everywhere!
谢谢  非常感谢 不谢 再见
- Thank you. Thank you very much. - Not at all.
很有趣的小家伙
What an amusing little fellow.
服务生
Waiter.
我真笨 什么?  亲爱的
- Oh, how silly of me. - What, dear?
我把皮夹子留在饭店
I've left my wallet in the hotel.
或许明天我们会在飞机上
Perhaps tomorrow we'll be on the plane.
“瑞克美式咖啡馆”
希特勒万岁!
再见到你真好  史查沙少校
It is good to see you again, Major Strasser.
谢谢  谢谢
Thank you, thank you.
让我来介绍雷诺队长 卡萨布兰卡的警察首长
May I present Captain Renault, police prefect of Casablanca.
史查沙少校
Major Strasser.
未被占据的法国属地 欢迎你来到卡萨布兰卡
Unoccupied France welcomes you to Casablanca.
谢谢  队长  来到这里真好
Thank you, captain. It's good to be here.
史查沙少校  这位是我的副官 卡箫副队长
Major Strasser, my aide, Lieutenant Casselle.
唐里尼队长 意大利军听候指示
Captain Tonnelli. The Italian service at your command.
下次吧  谢谢
That is kind of you.
(意大利文)
他听不明白你说什么 (法语)
你可能觉得 卡萨布兰卡的天气有一点暖
You may find the climate of Casablanca a trifle warm.
全德国人必须适应各种天气 从俄国到撒哈拉
We Germans must get used to all climates, from Russia to the Sahara.
或许你所指的不是天气 不然会是什么?  亲爱的少校
- Perhaps you werert referring to weather. - What else?
关于被谋杀的快递员 你们做了些什么?
The murder of the couriers. What has been done?
我的手下逮捕的疑犯人数是平常的两倍
My men are rounding up twice the usual number of suspects.
我们已知道凶手是谁 很好  我已在警方监管中吗?
- But we know already who the murderer is. - Good. Is he in custody?
不必急 今晚他会去瑞克咖啡馆
No hurry. Tonight he'll be at Rick's.
每个人都会去瑞克咖啡馆
Everybody comes to Rick's.
我已听说过这家咖啡馆 并且听说过瑞克他本人
I've already heard about this cafe. And also about Mr. Rick himself.
等待、等待、等待
Waiting, waiting, waiting.
我永远离不开这里了
I'll never get out of here.
我会死在卡萨布兰卡
I'll die in Casablanca.
可是你不能再加一点吗?
But can't you make it just a little more?
求求你
Please?
对不起  女士 可是钻石在市场上不易脱手
Sorry, but diamonds are a drug on the market. Everybody sells diamonds.
所有的人都在卖钻石 到处都是钻石  两千四百元
There are diamonds everywhere. 2400.
好吧
All right.
卡车准备好了  人手在等着 一切都...
The trucks are waiting. The men are waiting. Everything...
(德语)
是"圣地牙哥号" 渔船
It's the fishing smack Santiago.
明天晚上一点离开 这里  从麦地那号后第三艘船
It leaves at 1 tomorrow night, here from the end of La Medina. Third boat.
谢谢  谢谢 并带一万五千元法O现金
- Thank you. Thank you. - And bring 15,000 francs in cash.
记住  一定要现金
Remember, in cash.
不必愁，我们全都预备好了
(俄语)
开门  阿都 是的  教授先生
- Open up, Abdul. - Yes, professor.
先生 女士红色
先生黑色
服务生 是的  女士
- Waiter? - Yes, madame?
可否问瑞克要不要跟我们喝酒
Will you ask Rick if he'll have a drink with us?
女士  他从不跟顾客喝酒的 从来不  我从没见过
Madame, he never drinks with customers. Never. I have never seen it.
是什么原因?  使酒廊老板如此势利
What makes saloonkeepers so snobbish?
或许如果你告诉他 我在阿姆斯特丹 经营第二大银行
Perhaps if you told him I ran the second-largest banking house in Amsterdam.
第二大?  那不会叫瑞克刮目相看
Second largest? That wouldn't impress Rick.
阿姆斯特丹的头号银行家 现在是我们厨房的糕饼师傅
The leading banker in Amsterdam is now the pastry chef in our kitchen.
我们有值得盼望的事情了
We have something to look forward to.
而他爸爸是侍者
And his father is the bellboy.
给女士的 先生
“一千法O”
“好的，瑞克”
对不起
Excuse me.
对不起  先生 这是私人的房间
I'm sorry, sir. This is a private room.
好大胆  我知道里面在赌博  又不是秘密
Of all the nerve. Who do you think...? I know there is gambling in there.
你岂敢不让我进去  有什么麻烦?  这位先生
- You dare not keep me out. - Yes? What's the trouble?
从夏威夷到柏林每个赌场 我都去过
I have been in every gambling room between Honolulu and Berlin.
如果你认为 不该让我进这种赌场
And if you think I'm going to be kept out of a saloon like this,
你可是大错特错
you're much mistaken.
对不起 哈罗  瑞克
Excuse me, please. Hello, Rick.
你的现金在酒吧可以用
Your cash is good at the bar.
什么?  你知道我是谁吗?
What? Do you know who I am?
我知道 酒吧让你光顾算你走运
I do. You're lucky the bar is open to you.
可恶极了 我会向有关当局报告
This is outrageous! I shall report it to The Angriff.
看你刚才那样对待德国银行家
You know, watching you just now,
会以为你整辈子都在做这种事
one would think you've been doing this all your life.
是什么使你认为我没有?  没什么
- What makes you think I haven't? - Nothing.
不过你刚来卡萨布兰卡时我想 你想什么?
- But when you first came, I thought... - You thought what?
我有什么权利去想?
What right do I have to think?
我可以吗?
May I
那两名德国快递员真不幸 对不对
Too bad about those two German couriers, wasrt it?
他们走运了 昨天他们还是两名德国办事员
They got a lucky break. Yesterday they were just clerks...
而今天他们成了光荣的死者
...today they are the honored dead.
你是个很愤世嫉俗的人  瑞克  请原谅我这样说
You are a very cynical person, Rick, if you'll forgive me for saying so.
我原谅你
I forgive you.
谢谢  你可否跟我喝一杯 不
- Will you have a drink with me? - No.
我忘了  你从不跟任何人喝酒 请再给我一杯
I forgot, you never drink with... I'll have another, please.
你轻视我  对不对?
You despise me, don't you?
如果是我让你这样想 我大概是吧
If I gave you any thought, I probably would.
可是为什么?
But why?
你反对我所做的那种生意?
Do you object to the kind of business I do?
可是为那些可怜的难民想一想
But think of all those poor refugees...
如果我不帮他们必然困死这里
...who must rot in this place if I didn't help them.
那不算太坏  透过我的方法 我提供他们出境许可证
That's not so bad. Through ways of my own, I provide them with exit visas.
有代价的  尤佳迪  有代价的
For a price, Ugarte. For a price.
为那些付不起 雷诺开的价钱的可怜虫想想
But think of all the poor devils who can't meet Renault 's price.
我以半价替他们弄到手 这算寄生虫吗?
I get it for them for half. Is that so parasitic?
我不反对寄生虫 我反对折价的寄生虫
I don't mind a parasite. I object to a cut-rate one.
在今晚之后 所有的事情将成过去
Well, after tonight I will be through with the whole business.
我要离开卡萨布兰卡
And I' m leaving, finally, this Casablanca.
你的出境许可是向谁买的?  雷诺还是你自己?
Who did you bribe for your visa? Renault or yourself?
我自己觉得自己的价钱较合理
Myself. I found myself much more reasonable.
你看
Look, Rick.
知道这是什么吗?
Know what this is?
即使是你也从来没看过的东西
Something that even you have never seen.
过境信函 由戴高乐将军签名的
Letters of transit signed by General de Gaulle.
不能废止  甚至不能盘问
Cannot be rescinded. Not even questioned.
等一下
One moment.
今晚我会 以作梦也想不到的价钱卖出去
Tonight I' II be selling those for more money than I ever dreamed of.
然后  再见  卡萨布兰卡
And then, addio, Casablanca.
我在卡萨布兰卡有很多朋友 可是不晓得为什么
I have many a friend in Casablanca, but somehow, just because you despise me...
因为你轻视我 你是我唯一信任的人
...you are the only one I trust.
请你替我保管好吗?  多久?
Will you keep these for me, please?
或许一小时  或许久一点点
- For how long? - Perhaps an hour. Perhaps a little longer.
我不要放过夜
- I don't want them here overnight. - Don't be afraid of that.
别担心  请替我保管
Please keep them for me.
谢谢  我知道我可以信任你
Thank you. I knew I could trust you.
侍者  我正在等一些人
Waiter. I' II be expecting some people.
如果有谁找我  我会在这里
If anybody asks for me, I'll be right here.
瑞克
Rick...
我想你现在对我比较刮目相看
...I hope you're more impressed with me now.
请恕我失陪  我要跟你的轮盘 分享我的好运气
If you'll forgive me, I' II share my good luck with your roulette wheel.
等一下
Just a moment.
我听谣言说那两名德国快递员 身上带着过境信函
I heard a rumor those two German couriers were carrying letters of transit.
我也听过那谣言  可怜虫
I've heard that rumor too. Poor devils.
你说对了  尤佳迪 我是对你比较刮目相看了
You're right, Ugarte. I am a little more impressed with you.
哈罗  瑞克
- Hello, Rick. - Hello, Ferrari.
法拉利 "蓝鹦鹉" 的生意如何
How's business at the Blue Parrot?
很好  不过我想买你的咖啡馆
- Fine, but I' d like to buy your cafe. - It 's not for sale.
那是不卖的 你还没听我出价呢!  多少钱也不卖
- You haven't heard my offer. - It 's not for sale at any price.
你要多少才肯卖山姆 我不买卖人口
- What do you want for Sam? - I don't buy or sell human beings.
可惜 人是卡萨布兰卡主要商品
Too bad. That's Casablanca's leading commodity.
光只是难民 我们就能大赚一笔
In refugees alone we could make a fortune,
如果你跟我一起做黑市生意
if you'd work with me in the black market.
不妨你做你的  我做我的
Suppose you run your business and let me run mine.
我们不妨去问山姆 他喜欢改变一下
Suppose we ask Sam. Maybe he'd like to make a change.
我们不妨去问
Suppose we do.
我亲爱的瑞克 什么时候才明白
When will you realize...
在今天这个世界  孤立不再是项实际的政策
...that in this world today isolationism is no longer a practical policy?
法拉利想要你到蓝鹦鹉工作
Sam, Ferrari wants you to work for him at the Blue Parrot.
我喜欢这里
Oh, I like it fine here.
他出双倍我给你的薪水
- He'll double what I pay you.
可是我在这里赚的钱已没时间花
- I ain't got time to spend what I make here.
对不起
Sorry.
老板的私人存货
The boss's private stock...
因为  伊娃  我爱你 闭嘴
...because, Yvonne, I love you. - Oh, shut up.
好吧  为了你  我会闭嘴 因为  伊娃  我爱你
All right, all right. For you, I shut up, because, Yvonne, I love you.
一些德国人付了这张支票 可不可以?
Some Germans gave this check. Is it all right?
你昨晚到那里了?
Where were you last night?
那么久以前的事 我记不起来了
That's so long ago, I don't remember.
我今晚可以见到你吗?  我从不计划那么遥远的事
- Will I see you tonight? - I never make plans that far ahead.
再给我一杯
Give me another.
沙克  她已喝够了 别听他的  帮我倒满
- Sascha, she's had enough. - Don't listen to him. Fill it up.
伊娃我爱你  可是他付我薪水
Yvonne, I love you, but he pays me.
瑞克  我已厌倦你了 沙克  叫部计程车 是的
- Rick, I' m tired of having you... - Sascha, call a cab.
来吧  我们去拿你的外衣
- We're gonna get your coat. - Take your hands off me.
别碰我 你该回家  你喝的已够多了
You're going home. You've had a little too much to drink.
嘿  计程车
Hey, taxi.
你以为你是谁?  把我推来推去
Who do you think you are, pushing me around?
我真是傻瓜爱上你这种男人
I was a fool to fall for a man like you.
你送她沙克  要肯定她回到家
Go with her, Sascha. Be sure she gets home.
是的  老板 然后马上回来
And come right back.
是  老板
Yes, boss.
哈罗  瑞克 路易
- Hello, Rick. - Hello, Louis.
你真奢侈  这样把女人抛开
How extravagant you are, throwing away women.
有一天她们可能会渐渐消失
Someday they may be scarce.
我想现在我该去拜访伊娃
I think now I shall pay a call on Yvonne.
或许可藉反作用占到便宜
Maybe get her on the rebound.
一讲到女人 你就是不折不扣的民主党
When it comes to women, you're a true democrat.
(法语)
如果他听得明白一个字 意大利将大获全胜
If he gets a word in, it'll be a major Italian victory.
往里斯本的飞机
The plane to Lisbon.
你会想坐在里面
You would like to be on it?
为什么?  里斯本有什么好?
Why? What's in Lisbon?
到美国的快航
The clipper to America.
我常思索为什么你不返回美国
I've often speculated on why you don't return to America.
你卷走教堂的基金逃吗?  你跟参议员的太太私奔?
Did you abscond with the church funds? Did you run off with a senator's wife?
我喜欢想像你杀了人 这满足我浪漫的遐想
Llike to think you killed a man. It's the romantic in me.
是三者的综合
It's a combination of all three.
到底是什么带你到卡萨布兰卡
And what in heavers name brought you to Casablanca?
我的健康  我来卡萨布兰卡 是为了这地方的水
My health. I came to Casablanca for the waters.
水?  什么水?  我们在沙漠里
The waters? What waters? We're in the desert.
我的消息错误
I was misinformed.
对不起!  瑞克先生
Excuse me, Monsieur Rick.
里面一位先生赢了两万块法O
A gentleman inside has won 20,000 francs...
出纳需要一些钱
...and the cashier would like some money.
我从保险柜拿
I'll get it from the safe.
我好难过  瑞克先生
I'm so upset, Rick. You know l- -
别提了  艾米 这种事常常发生
Forget it, Emil. Mistakes like that happen all the time.
我非常抱歉
I'm awfully sorry.
瑞克 今晚这里会有点刺激的事
Rick, there will be some excitement here tonight.
我们将在你的咖啡馆逮捕人
An arrest in your cafe.
什么?  又一次?  这不是普通的逮捕
- Again? - This is no ordinary arrest.
是谋杀犯
A murderer, no less.
如果你想要警告他 别让自己不方便 你逃不过监视的
If you're thinking of warning him, don't put yourself out. He cannot escape.
我不为任何人冒险的 明智的外交政策
- I stick my neck out for nobody. - A wise foreign policy.
(法语)
我们本可以在今晚较早时 在蓝鹦鹉进行逮捕
Could have made the arrest earlier, at the Blue Parrot.
为了表示我对你的敬意 我们在这里进行
Out of my regard for you, we're staging it here.
可以带给你的顾客一点娱乐
It will amuse your customers.
我们的娱乐节目已经够多了
Our entertainment's enough.
瑞克  今晚我们这里有名贵客
We're to have an important guest here tonight.
第三帝国的史查沙少校
Major Strasser of the Third Reich, no less.
我们进行逮捕时希望他在场
We want him to be here when we make the arrest.
以示范一下我办事的效率
A demonstration of the efficiency of my administration.
我明白 史查沙来这里干什么?
I see. And what's Strasser doing here?
他不可能老远来到卡萨布兰卡
He certainly didn't come here...
为了目击你的办事效率吧?
...to witness a demonstration of your efficiency.
或许不是 拿去吧
- Perhaps not. - Here.
不会再发生了 没关系
- It shall not happen again. - That's all right.
我知道你心里有事情 何不直接说出来?
Louis, you got something on your mind. Why don't you spill it.
你观察力真好
How observant you are.
事实上我想劝告你一声
As a matter of fact, I wanted to give you a word of advice.
是吗?
Yeah?
要喝白兰地吗?  谢谢
- Have a brandy? - Thank you.
瑞克  在这咖啡馆里 有很多出境证卖出去
There are many exit visas sold in this cafe,
不过我们知道你一张也没卖过
but we know that you've never sold one.
所以我们才准许你营业
That is the reason we permit you to remain open.
我还以为是我让你在轮盘赢钱
I thought it was because llet you win at roulette.
那是另一个原因
That is another reason.
有一个要前往美国的人 已抵达卡萨布兰卡
There is a man arrived in Casablanca on his way to America.
他会给任何提供他出境证的人 一大笔钱
He will offer a fortune to anyone who'll furnish an exit visa.
他叫什么名字?  维多拉斯路
- What's his name? - Victor Laszlo.
维多拉斯路?
Victor Laszlo?
瑞克  这是我第一次看到 有人如此令你着迷
Rick, that is the first time I've seen you so impressed.
半个地球的人都为他着迷
He's succeeded in impressing half the world.
我的责任就是阻止 另一半的地球人不再为他着迷
It's my duty to see that he doesn't impress the other half.
瑞克  拉斯路绝不能踏足美国 他要留在卡萨布兰卡
Laszlo must never reach America. He stays in Casablanca.
看他如何达成将很有趣
It'll be interesting to see how he manages.
达成什么?  他的逃亡
- Manages what? - His escape.
我刚才告诉你...
- But I just told you... - Stop it.
够了  他从集中营逃出来 纳粹党在欧洲到处追捕他
He escaped from a concentration camp. The Nazis have chased him all over Europe.
这是追捕的最终站
This is the end of the chase.
赌两万法O  不是
Twenty thousand francs says it isn't.
这是认真的吗?
Is that a serious offer?
我刚赔了两万  我想赚回来
I just paid out 20, and I' d like to get it back.
加到十万吧!  我只是个贫穷的腐败官吏
Make it 10. I'm only a poor corrupt official.
好吧 成交
- Okay. - Done.
不管他多聪明 他仍然需要一份出境许可证
No matter how clever he is, he still needs an exit visa.
或许我该说是两份
Or I should say two.
为什么是两份?  他跟一位女士一起旅行
- Why two? - He is traveling with a lady.
一份他也会要的 我不认为  我看过那位女士
- He'll take one. - I think not. I' ve seen the lady.
如果他没把她留在马赛或奥朗
And if he did not leave her in Marseilles or Oran...
肯定不会把她留在卡萨布兰卡
...he certainly won't leave her in Casablanca.
或许他没有你那么浪漫
Maybe he's not quite as romantic as you are.
都一样  他不会拿到出境证
It doesn't matter. There is no exit visa for him.
是什么使你觉得我可能有兴趣 帮忙拉斯路逃亡
What ever gave you the impression that I might help Laszlo escape?
因为  亲爱的瑞克 我怀疑在那愤世嫉俗的外表下
Because, my dear Ricky, I suspect that under that cynical shell...
你的内心是个性情中人
...you are at heart a sentimentalist.
你要笑随便你 不过我凑巧熟知你的记录
Laugh if you will, but I happen to be familiar with your record.
让我举出两项
Let me point out just two items:
在1935年 你运枪械到衣索匹亚
In 1935, you ran guns to Ethiopia.
在1936年  你在西班牙 替反佛朗哥派打仗
In 1936, you fought in Spain on the Loyalist side.
二次我都得到丰厚的酬劳
And got well paid for it on both occasions.
胜方本可以给你更好的酬劳
The winning side would have paid you much better.
或许吧
Maybe.
似乎你坚决 要把拉斯路留在这里
It seems you're determined to keep Laszlo here.
我奉命行事
I have my orders.
我明白了  德国秘密警察
I see. Gestapo spank.
亲爱的瑞克 你高估了秘密警察的影响力了
My dear Ricky, you overestimate the influence of the Gestapo.
我不干涉他们 他们也不干涉我
I don't interfere with them, and they don't interfere with me.
在卡萨布兰卡 我掌握自己的命运
In Casablanca, I am master of my fate.
史查沙少校来了  长官
- I am... - Major Strasser is here, sir.
才刚说完 失陪
- You were saying? - Excuse me.
卡尔 给史查沙少校最好的位子 靠近女士们的
Carl, see that Major Strasser gets a good table, close to the ladies.
我已经给他最好的了
I have already given him the best,
知道他是德国人 反正他一定接受
knowing he is German and would take it anyway.
静静地逮捕的 每个门口派两个守卫
Take him quietly. Two guards at every door.
一切都准备好了  长官 去吧
- Everything is ready, sir. - Go ahead.
晚安  先生 晚安  队长
- Good evening, gentlemen. - Good evening, captain.
要一块坐吗?  谢谢
- Wort you join us? - Thank you.
很荣幸你光临本店 香槟和鱼子酱
- It 's a pleasure to have you here, major. - Champagne and a tin of caviar.
容我推荐华提可 很好的法国酒
May I recommend Veuve Clicquot '26, a good French wine.
谢谢 好的  先生
Very well, sir.
很有趣的俱乐部 特别是今晚  长官
- A very interesting club. - Especially so tonight, major.
在几分钟后你将会看到 那个谋杀你快递员的人
In a few minutes you'll see the arrest of the man who murdered your couriers.
我正期待如此  队长
I expected no less, captain.
尤佳迪先生
Monsieur Ugarte.
请你跟我们走!  当然
- Will you please come with us? - Certainly.
我可否先把筹码换回现金?
May I first please cash my chips?
运气不错呢 两千  麻烦你 两千
Very lucky, huh? Two thousand, please.
瑞克  瑞克  救我
Rick! Rick, help me!
别傻了  你逃不掉的 瑞克  把我藏起来  想办法
- Don't be a fool. You can't get away. - But, Rick, hide me. Do something!
非常好  队长
Excellent, captain.
当他们来抓我时 希望你多尽点力
When they come for me, I hope you'll be more of a help.
我不为任何人冒险
I stick my neck out for nobody.
很抱歉有点骚乱  各位 不过全过去了  一切平安无事
I'm sorry there was a disturbance, folks, but it's all over now.
尽管坐下来  尽情享受 好了  山姆 好的  老板
Just sit down and have a good time. Enjoy yourselves. All right, Sam.
瑞克  这位是第三帝国的 海米勒史查沙少校
Rick, this is Major Heinrich Strasser of the Third Reich.
你好吗?  瑞克先生 你好吗?
- How do you do, Mr. Rick? - How do you do?
你已经认识的 第三帝国的哈斯先生
You already know Herr Heinze of the Third Reich.
请一块坐  瑞克先生
Please join us, Mr. Rick.
今晚我们非常荣幸
We are very honored tonight.
第三帝国的名声 部分是史查沙少校的功劳
Major Strasser is one of the reasons the Third Reich enjoys the reputation it has.
他一直重复第三帝国 好像你预料会有别的一样
You repeat Third Reich as though you expected there to be others.
少校  私底下我会来者不拒
Well, personally, major, I will take what comes.
你介意我问你一些问题吗?
Do you mind if I ask you a few questions?
当然  非正式的 如果你喜欢大可正式的问
- Unofficially, of course. - Make it official if you like.
你的国籍是什么?  我是个醉酒鬼
- What is your nationality? - I' m a drunkard.
那使瑞克成为世界公民
And that makes Rick a citizen of the world.
我在纽约市出生 如果这对你有帮助
I was born in New York City, if that'll help you any.
我知道你在巴黎被占领时 从巴黎来到这里
I understand you came here from Paris at the time of the occupation.
那似乎不是什么秘密
There seems to be no secret about that.
你是不是那些无法想像心爱的巴黎
Are you one of those people...
被德国人进占的人其中之一
...who cannot imagine the Germans in their beloved Paris?
我没有特别钟情巴黎
It's not particularly my beloved Paris.
你能想像我们占据伦敦吗?
Can you imagine us in London?
你到那里之后再问我吧
When you get there, ask me.
有外交手腕
Diplomatist.
那纽约呢?
How about New York?
在纽约有某些区域  我不会建议你尝试侵入
There are sections of New York, major that I wouldn't advise you to try to invade.
你认为谁会打胜仗?  我一点也不清楚
- Who do you think will win the war? - I haven't the slightest idea.
瑞克对一切都采中立态度
Rick is completely neutral about everything.
他并非一直那么小心保持中立 我们有你的完整档案
You were not always so carefully neutral. We have a complete dossier on you.
理查宾勒  美国人  三十七岁 不能返回本国
"Richard Blaine, American. Age: 37. Cannot return to his country."
原因有点含糊 我们也知道你在巴黎做什么
The reason is a little vague. We also know what you did in Paris.
也知道你为何离开巴黎  别担心  我们不会拿去广播
And also we know why you left Paris. Don't worry, we're not going to broadcast it.
对女人方面也一样
And that takes in the field of women too.
我的眼睛真的是棕色吗?
Are my eyes really brown?
请原谅我的好奇心  宾勒先生  重点是
You will forgive my curiosity, Mr. Blaine. The point is...
帝国的一位敌人 已来到卡萨布兰卡
...an enemy of the Reich has come to Casablanca...
我们正查问任何能帮我们的人
...and we are checking up on anybody who can be of any help to us.
我对拉斯路去留与否的兴趣 纯粹是赌博的关系
My interest in whether Victor Laszlo stays or goes is purely a sporting one.
这样说来 你对奸诈的狐狸毫不同情
In this case you have no sympathy for the fox?
不特别同情 我也了解猎犬的立场
Not particularly. I understand the point of view of the hound too.
维多拉斯路在布拉格的报纸 刊登最无耻的谎言
Laszlo published the foulest lies in the Prague newspapers...
一直到我们进占那一天 甚至在之后还有
...until the day we marched in.
他在一地窖中 继续印毁损的传单
And even after that, he continued to print scandal sheets in his cellar.
当然  不得不承认他勇气可嘉
Of course, one must admit he has great courage.
我承认他很聪明 在巴黎他三次逃过我们的掌心
I admit he's clever. Three times he slipped through our fingers.
他继续他的活动 我们决意不让这种事再发生
In Paris he continued his activities. We intend not to let it happen again.
对不起  你们的生意是政治 而我的生意是经营酒馆
Excuse me, gentlemen. Your business is politics, mine is running a saloon.
晚安  宾勒先生
Good evening, Mr. Blaine.
你看到了  少校 瑞克你一点也不必担心
You see, major? You have nothing to worry about Rick.
或许吧
Perhaps.
我订了一个位子  维多拉斯路  -拉斯路先生  这边走
- I reserved a table. Victor Laszlo. - Yes, Monsieur Laszlo. Right this way.
两杯"君度"  麻烦你
Two Cointreaux, please.
我没看到尤佳迪形容的人
I saw no one of Ugarte's description.
维多 我感觉我们不该留在这里
Victor, I feel somehow we shouldn't stay here.
如果我们现在走出去 只会引人注目
If we would walk out so soon it would only call attention to us.
或许尤佳迪在咖啡馆的另一边
Perhaps Ugarte is in some other part of the cafe.
对不起  你们像是 正要前往美国的夫妇
Excuse me, but you look like a couple who are on their way to America.
在那里这戒指会有市场
You'll find a market there for this ring.
我被迫卖掉它是个巨大的牺牲
I'm forced to sell it at a great sacrifice.
谢谢  我没想过买  或许买给女士
- Thank you, but I hardly think... - Perhaps for the lady.
这戒指独一无二
The ring is quite unique.
好  我很感兴趣 好
- Yes, I' m very interested. - Good.
你叫什么名字?
What is your name?
贝加  挪威人  听候差遣
Berger, Norwegian. At your service, sir.
维多
几分钟后我在酒吧跟你会面
I'll meet you in a few minutes at the bar.
不  我不想买戒指 谢谢你给我们看
We don't want the ring, but thanks for showing it to us.
那么便宜  不过你决定了 对不起  我决定了
- Such a bargain. But that is your decision? - I' m sorry, it is.
是拉斯路先生吗?  是
- Monsieur Laszlo, is it not? - Yes?
我是雷诺队长  警察首长
I am Captain Renault, prefect of police.
是  你想要什么?
Yes, what is it you want?
我欢迎你来到卡萨布兰卡 并祝你在这里住得愉快
Merely to welcome you to Casablanca and wish you a pleasant stay.
我们并不常有这么特出的访客
It isn't often we have so distinguished a visitor.
谢谢  我希望你原谅我  队长
Thank you. I hope you'll forgive me, captain.
目前的法国行政当局 并非一直那么友善
The present French administration hasn't always been so cordial.
容我介绍伊莎琳小姐
May I present Miss llsa Lund.
我听说你是卡萨布兰卡有史以来最美丽的女访客
I was told you were the most beautiful woman ever to visit Casablanca.
那是粗略又保守的说法
That was a gross understatement.
你太客气了
You're very kind.
－一起坐吧 -如果你准许我
- Wort you join us? - Lf you will permit me.
艾米  给我一瓶最好的香槟 记在我的帐上
Oh, no, Emile, please. A bottle of your best champagne. And put it on my bill.
好的，先生 队长
先生  这是我们玩的一种游戏
It's a game we play.
他们记在帐单上 我撕毁帐单非常方便
They put it on the bill, I tear up the bill. It is very convenient.
队长  弹琴的那个人
Captain, the boy who's playing the piano...
我好像在那里看过
Somewhere I' ve seen him.
山姆?  是
- Sam? - Yes.
他跟瑞克一起从巴黎来
He came from Paris with Rick.
瑞克?  他是谁?
Rick? Who is he?
女士  你正在瑞克咖啡馆 瑞克是... 他是什么?
- Mademoiselle, you are in Rick's. Rick is... - Is what?
女士  他是那种... 如果我是女人的话
Mademoiselle, he's the kind of man that, well, if I were a woman...
我应该会爱上他的男人
...and I were not around, I should be in love with Rick.
我真是个傻瓜 我对一位美丽女人说别的男人
But what a fool I am talking to a beautiful woman about another man.
失陪 少校
Excuse me. Major.
林小姐 拉斯路先生  让我介绍 海米勒史查沙少校
Mademoiselle Lund and Monsieur Laszlo, may I present Major Strasser.
你好吗?
How do you do?
我盼望这份荣幸很久了
This is a pleasure I have looked forward to.
我肯定你会原谅我不够亲切
I'm sure you'll excuse me if I' m not gracious.
不过你明白  史查沙少校 我是捷克人
You see, Major Strasser, I am a Czechoslovakian.
你以前的捷克人 现在 你是第三帝国统治下的人民
You were a Czechoslovakian. Now you are a subject of the German Reich.
我从不曾接受这份优待 而现在我站在法国的土地上
I have never accepted that privilege. And I' m now on French soil.
我想跟你讨论一下 你在法国土地上引起的问题
I should like to discuss some matters arising from your presence on French soil.
时间和地点都不太适当
This is hardly the time or place.
那我们另订时间和地点好了 明天十点在首长的办公室
Then we shall state another time and place. Tomorrow at 10 in the prefect's office.
好吗?  小姐
With mademoiselle.
雷诺队长  我在你管辖之下
Captain, I am under your authority.
到你的办公室是你的命令吗?
Is it your order that we come to your office?
让我说这是我的请求好了 那样的字眼比较好听
Let us say it is my request. That is a much more pleasant word.
好吧 小姐
Very well.
后会有期
很聪明的策略性让步  少校
A very clever tactical retreat, major.
这一次他们决意要阻止我 维多  我替你感到害怕
- This time they really mean to stop me. - Victor, I' m afraid for you.
我们以前也曾身处困境 不是吗?
We've been in difficult places before, haven't we?
我必须查出贝加知道的事
I must find out what Berger knows.
小心点 我会
- Be careful. - I will. Don't worry.
贝加先生 那戒指我可以再看吗?  可以 先生
Monsieur Berger, the ring. Could I see it again?
请来一杯香槟鸡尾酒
Champagne cocktail, please.
我从报上的照片认得你的相貌 拉斯路先生
I recognize you from the news photographs, Monsieur Laszlo.
在集中营里想不消瘦也很难
In a concentration camp, one is apt to lose a little weight.
我们看过五次报导你被杀死 在五个不同的地方
We read five times that you were killed in five different places.
每一次都是真实的
As you see, it was true every single time.
谢天谢地  我找到你  贝加
Thank heaven I found you, Berger.
我在找一个叫尤佳迪的人 他预定是要帮我的
I'm looking for a man by the name of Ugarte. He's supposed to help me.
尤佳迪自身难保
Ugarte cannot even help himself.
他因谋杀罪被逮捕了 他今晚在这里被捕的
He's under arrest for murder. He was arrested here tonight.
我明白了
I see.
不过我们还是自由之身 我们可以尽力 我们有组织
But we who are still free will do all we can. We are organized.
在地下  就像其他地方一样
Underground, like everywhere else.
明天晚上有一个会议
Tomorrow night there is a meeting at the Caverne du Bois.
如果你会来... 先生
If you will come...
可否请弹钢琴的过来一下?
Will you ask the piano player to come over here?
好的  小姐
Very well, mademoiselle.
珠宝生意如何?  贝加 不太好  请替我结帐
- How's the jewelry business, Berger? - Not so good. Check, please.
真可惜你不早点来这里
Too bad you werert here earlier.
今天晚上我们有一点刺激呢?  对不对?  贝加
We had quite a bit of excitement, didn't we, Berger?
对  失陪
Yes. Excuse me, gentlemen.
我的帐单 不用 两杯香槟鸡尾酒  拜托
- My bill. - No. Two champagne cocktails. Please.
哈罗  山姆 哈罗  小姐
- Hello, Sam. - Hello, Miss llsa.
我从没想过会再看到你
I never expected to see you again.
已经很久了
It's been a long time.
是的  小姐 过去的事有如逝水
Yes, ma'am. Alot of water under the bridge.
来一些旧日的歌  山姆 是  小姐
- Some of the old songs, Sam. - Yes, ma'am.
瑞克在那里?
Where is Rick?
我不知道  我整晚没看到他
I don't know. I ain't seen him all night.
他什么时候回来?  今晚不会  他不会回来
- When will he be back? - Not tonight no more. He ain't coming...
他回家了
He went home.
他常常这么早就走吗?  他从不
- Does he always leave so early? - He never...
他有位女友在蓝鹦鹉
Well, he's got a girl up to the Blue Parrot.
他常常上那儿
Goes up there all the time.
你以前比较会撒谎  山姆
You used to be a much better liar, Sam.
别去打扰他  伊莎小姐 你为他带来恶运
Leave him alone, Miss llsa. You're bad luck to him.
弹一次  山姆  看在往日份上
Play it once, Sam. For old times' sake.
我不知道你是什么意思?  伊莎小姐
I don't know what you mean, Miss llsa.
弹吧  山姆
Play it, Sam.
弹"时光飞逝"
Play "As Time Goes By."
我记不起来了  伊莎小姐 我有点生锈了
I can't remember it, Miss llsa. I'm a little rusty on it.
我替你哼调子
I'll hum it for you.
唱出来  山姆
Sing it, Sam.
山姆 我想我告诉过你永远别弹
Sam, I thought I told you never to play...
你刚才问及瑞克  他来了 林小姐  让我来介绍
Well, you were asking about Rick, and here he is. May I present...
哈罗  伊莎 哈罗  瑞克
- Hello, llsa. - Hello, Rick.
你已经认识瑞克了  小姐 那  或许你也...
Oh, you've already met Rick, mademoiselle? Then perhaps you also...
这位是拉斯路先生
This is Mr. Laszlo.
你好吗?  你好
- How do you do? - How do you do?
在卡萨布兰卡听到很多你的事
One hears a great deal about Rick in Casablanca.
而维多拉斯路的事到处可闻
And about Victor Laszlo everywhere.
跟我们喝一杯好吗?  不  瑞克从不...
- Wort you join us for a drink? - Rick never...
谢谢  我会
- Thanks, I will. - Well...
一项惯例打破了  艾米!
...a precedent is being broken. Emile.
这是很别致的咖啡馆 我恭喜你 我恭喜你
- Interesting cafe. I congratulate you. - I congratulate you.
为了什么?  你的工作
- What for? - Your work.
谢谢  我尽力而为
Thank you. I try.
人家都尽力而为  而你成功了
We all try. You succeed.
我不太明白你们两个 她早先在问关于你的事
She was asking about you earlier,
那种态度使我非常嫉妒
Rick, in a way that made me extremely jealous.
我不肯定是你
I wasrt sure you were the same.
我想想看 我们最后一次见面是 "美丽的晨晕"
- Let's see, the last time we met... - Was La Belle Aurore.
太好了  你记得
How nice. You remembered.
不过那天正好是德国军队 开进巴黎的日子
But, of course, that was the day the Germans marched into Paris.
不容易忘记的日子 不容易
Not an easy day to forget.
我记得每一个细节 德国人穿灰色  你穿蓝色
I remember every detail. The Germans wore gray, you wore blue.
对  我把那件衣服收起来了
Yes. I put that dress away.
当德国人撤离后  我会再穿
When the Germans march out I'll wear it again.
瑞克  你变得较人性化了 我猜我们必须感谢你
Ricky, you're becoming quite human. I suppose we have to thank you for that.
伊莎  我不想扫兴 不过时候不早了
Ilsa, I don't wish to be the one to say it, but it's late.
的确是  在卡萨布兰卡有戒严
So it is. We have a curfew in Casablanca.
警察首长可不能被发现喝醉酒神智不清
It would never do for the chief of police to be found drinking after hours.
我希望你不介意 一点也不
- I hope we didn't overstay our welcome. - Not at all.
你的帐单  先生 让我付 我请客
- Your check, sir. - It 's my party.
又一个惯例打破了 这是一个很有趣的晚上
Another precedent gone. This has been a very interesting evening.
我替你叫计程车 在晚上汽油要配给
I'll call you a cab. Gasoline rationing, time of night.
我们会再来 随时欢迎
- We'll come again. - Anytime.
替我跟山姆说晚安 我会
- Say good night to Sam for me. - I will.
世界上没有人能像山姆那样 弹"时光飞逝"
There's still nobody in the world who can play "As Time Goes By" like Sam.
他有好久没弹这首歌了
He hasn't played it in a long time.
晚安 晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
晚安
Night.
这个瑞克叫人莫名其妙 他是什么人?
A very puzzling fellow, this Rick. What sort is he?
我也说不上来 虽然在巴黎我常看到他
I really can't say, though I saw him quite often in Paris.
明天十点在首长的办公室 我们会去的 晚安
- Tomorrow at 10, at the prefect office. - We'll be there.
晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
老板
Boss?
老板 是
- Boss? - Yeah?
你要不要上床睡?  现在不要
- Boss, ain't you going to bed? - Not right now.
你会在短时间内上床睡吗?
Ain't you planning on going to bed in the near future?
晚一点你会上床睡吗?  不
- You ever going to bed? - No.
我也不困
Well, I ain't sleepy, either.
好  来喝一杯吧
Good, then have a drink.
不  我不要  老板 那就别喝
- Not me, boss. - Then don't have a drink.
老板  我们离开这里吧
Boss, let's get out of here.
不  山姆  我在等一位女士
No, sir. I' m waiting for a lady.
拜托  我们走吧 这里除了麻烦之外什么也没有
Please, let's go. Ain't nothing but trouble for you here.
她回来了  我知道她回来了
She's coming back. I know she's coming back.
我们开车去  开一整个晚上
We'll take the car and drive all night.
我们去喝酒 我们也可去钓鱼  躲开一下 直到她离开
We'll get drunk. We'll go fishing, stay away until she's gone.
闭嘴  回家去好吗?  不  先生  我要留在这里
- Shut up and go home, will you? - No, sir, I' m staying right here.
他们抓了尤佳迪 然后她走进来
They grab Ugarte, then she walks in.
自然法则  一进一出
That's the way it goes. One in, one out.
山姆 是的  老板
- Sam. - Yes, boss?
卡萨布兰卡现在是1941年12月  在纽约是什么时候?
If it's December 1941 in Casablanca, what time is it in New York?
什么?
What?
我的手表停了
My watch stopped.
我打赌在纽约他们都睡着了
I bet they're asleep in New York.
我打赌全美国的人都睡着了
I bet they're asleep all over America.
全世界有那么多城镇 有那么多酒吧
Of all the gin joints in all the towns in all the world...
她就走进我这一家
...she walks into mine.
你在弹什么?  只是我随便乱弹的
- What's that you're playing? - A little something of my own.
停  你知道我想听什么 不  我不知道
- Well, stop it. You know what I want to hear. - No, I don't.
你能为她弹  你也能为我弹
You played it for her. You can play it for me.
我想我记不起来 如果她受得了  我也可以
- I don't think I can remember... - lf she can stand it, I can.
弹!
Play it.
是的  老板
Yes, boss.
你到底是什么人?  你以前是什么?
Who are you really? And what were you before?
你是做什么的?  你又想些什么?
What did you do, and what did you think?
我们说过不准问问题
We said no questions.
永志不忘
Here's looking at you, kid.
一法O买你的心事
A franc for your thoughts.
在美国他们只出一分钱
In America they'd bring only a penny.
我猜大概只值这么多
I guess that's about all they're won'th.
我愿意被超额收费 告诉我
I'm willing to be overcharged. Tell me.
我在想...
Well, I was wondering...
为什么我那么幸运?
Why I'm so lucky.
为什么你会在那里等着我出现  正巧又被我找到
Why I should find you waiting for me to come along.
为什么我的生命中 没有别的男人?
Why there is no other man in my life?
那很简单  以前有
That's easy. There was.
他死了
He's dead.
对不起我问了
I'm sorry for asking.
我忘了我们说过不准问问题
I forgot we said no questions.
只有一个答案 能解答我们所有的问题
Only one answer can take care of all our questions.
“巴黎”
这里是德国人史特格
法国人，巴黎人
法国军队已放弃他们的岗位
德国人已要求进入首都
现在什么也阻止不了他们了
Nothing can stop them now.
星期三  最迟星期四 他们便会来巴黎
Wednesday, Thursday at the latest, they'll be in Paris.
理查  如果他们发现你的过去 你留在这里便不安全了
Richard, they'll find out your record. You won't be safe here.
我早已在他们的黑名单上了 荣誉栏上
I'm on their blacklist already. Their roll of honor.
亨利要我们喝完这一瓶
Henri wants us to finish this bottle and then three more.
还有三瓶他要用来浇花 也不让德国人喝
Says he'll water his garden with champagne before he'll let the Germans drink it.
这可以减轻被占领的苦恼 你说是不是?  理查先生
This sort of takes the sting out of being occupied, doesn't it?
你说对了
You said it.
永志不忘
Here's looking at you, kid.
(德语)
我的德语有点生锈了
My Germars a little rusty.
是秘密警察
It's the Gestapo.
他们说预计明天到巴黎
They say they expect to be in Paris tomorrow.
他们在教我们当他们进来时 该如何反应
They're telling us how to act when they come marching in.
整个世界快倒下来了 我们却挑上这时候来谈恋爱
With the whole world crumbling, we pick this time to fall in love.
对  真不巧
It's pretty bad timing.
在十年前的话  你会说什么?  十年前?
- Where were you, say, 10 years ago? - 10 years ago?
我想想看
Let's see.
我还带着牙套 那时候你在那儿?
Yes, I was having a brace put on my teeth. Where were you?
正在找工作
Looking for a job.
那是炮火吗?
Was that cannon fire?
还是我的心在跳?
Or is it my heart pounding?
那是新的德国77型 单以声音来判断 大约只有35哩远
It's the new German 77th, and judging by the sound, only about 35 miles away.
越来越近了
And getting closer every minute.
来  来  喝光
Here, here, drink up.
另外那三瓶我们喝不完了
We'll never finish the other three.
德国人很快就会到了 他们会来找你
Them Germans will be here pretty soon, and they'll come looking for you.
别忘了拿下你有悬赏
And don't forget, there's a price on your head.
我在公寓留有字条 他们知道到那里能找到我
Ileft a note in my apartment. They'll know where to find me.
奇怪
It's strange.
我对你了解得那么少  我对你的了解更少
- I know so very little about you. - I know very little about you.
只知道你矫正过牙齿
Just the fact that you had your teeth straightened.
认真点  亲爱的  你有危险 你一定要离开巴黎
Be serious, darling. You are in danger. You must leave Paris.
不  不  我们一定要离开
No, we must leave.
对  当然是我们
Yes, of course. We.
往马赛的火车五点开出 我四点半到你的饭店接你
The train for Marseilles leaves at 5:00. I'll pick you up at your hotel at 4:30.
不  不要在我饭店  我...
Not at my hotel. I...
在我离开前我在城里有事要办
I have things to do in the city before I leave.
我会在火车站跟你碰面
I'll meet you at the station.
好吧  四点四十五分
All right, at a quarter to 5.
我们何不在马赛结婚
Why don't we get married in Marseilles?
现在计划不嫌太遥远吗?
That's too far ahead to plan.
对  我猜是远了点
Yes. I guess it is too far ahead.
那火车上的列车长如何
Let's see... What about the engineer?
他可以在火车上替我们主持婚礼
Why can't he marry us on the train?
亲爱的 为什么不?  船上的船长可以 似乎有点不公平
Why not? The captain on a ship can. It doesn't seem fair that...
怎么了?  孩子
Hey, what's wrong, kid?
我那么爱你
Llove you so much.
而我那么痛恨这战争
And I hate this war so much.
这是个疯狂的世界 任何事都可能发生
It's a crazy world. Anything can happen.
万一如果你不能离开
If you shouldn't get away...
我是说  万一我们被分开
If something should keep us apart...
不管他们把你安置在那里
...wherever they put you...
不管我会在那里 我要你知道我...
...and wherever I' II be, I want you to know that I...
吻我
Kiss me.
有如最后一次般吻我
Kiss me as if it were the last time.
上车!  上车!
注意!  上车!
所有乘客上车 最后一班火车在三分钟后开出
快点，上车!  最后一班火车!
她在那里?  你有看到她吗?
Where is she? Have you seen her?
不  理查先生  我找不到她 她已经退了房间
I can't find her. She checked out of the hotel.
不过你刚离开后送来这字条
But this note came just after you left.
“亲爱的理查”
“我不能跟你走或是再见你”
“你不要问为什么”
“只要相信我爱你”
“给我的爱人愿上帝祝福你”
“伊莎”
那是最后的召唤  理查先生
That's the last call, Mr. Richard.
你听到我说吗?
Do you hear me?
快点  我们离开这里再说 快点  理查先生  快点
Come on, Mr. Richard. Let's get out of here. Come on.
瑞克  我必须跟你谈一下
Rick, I have to talk to you.
我把第一杯留下来跟你一起喝 在这儿
I saved my first drink to have with you. Here.
不  不  瑞克  今晚不行 特别是今晚
- No, Rick. Not tonight. - Especially tonight.
为什么你一定要来卡萨布兰卡 还有很多别的地方
Why did you have to come to Casablanca? There are other places.
如果我知道你在这里 我就不会来
I wouldn't have come if I' d known you were here.
相信我  那是真的 我并不知道
Believe me, Rick, it's true. I didn't know.
奇怪的是你的声音 一点都没变 我仍然听得到
It's funny about your voice, how it hasn't changed. I can still hear it.
亲爱的理查 我会随你到天涯海角
"Richard, dear, I'll go with you anyplace.
我们一起坐上火车 一路不停 别这样  瑞克
- We'll get on a train and never stop." - Don't, Rick.
我明白你的感受
I can understand how you feel.
你明白我的感受
You understand how I feel.
我们相叙的日子有多长?  亲爱的
How long was it we had, honey?
我没有数 我有
- I didn't count the days. - Well, I did.
每一天都有
Every one of them.
最后一天我记得最清楚
Mostly I remember the last one.
当汽笛声响过后 月台上有一个人站在雨中
The wild finish. A guy standing on a station platform in the rain...
脸上挂着可笑的表情
...with a comical look on his face...
因为他的内心被踢翻了
...because his insides have been kicked out.
瑞克 我可否说一个故事给你听?
Can I tell you a story, Rick?
结局也有汽笛声吗?
Does it got a wild finish?
我还不知道结局
I don't know the finish yet.
那就说出来 或许一边说可以一边想
Go on, tell it. Maybe one'll come to you as you go along.
是有关一位女孩 她刚从科斯鲁来到巴黎
It's about a girl who had just come to Paris from her home in Oslo.
在一个朋友的家里
At the house of some friends...
她遇到她听闻了一辈子的男人
...she met a man about whom she'd heard her whole life.
一个伟大又勇敢的男人
A very great and courageous man.
他为她揭开一个由知识
He opened up for her a whole beautiful world...
思想和理想组成的美丽世界
...full of knowledge and thoughts and ideals.
她知道的一切  她的成长 都是由于他的关系
Everything she knew or ever became was because of him.
她景仰他
And she looked up to him...
崇拜他
...and worshiped him...
她假定那就是爱的感觉
...with a feeling she supposed was love.
对  很美
Yes, that's very pretty.
我也听过一个故事 事实上在我的年代也听过很多故事
I heard a story once. In fact, I've heard a lot of stories in my time.
都由细小的钢琴叮叮声伴奏
They went along with the sound of a tinny piano...
就在楼下的大厅弹奏
...playing in the parlor downstairs.
先生  我小时候有一次 遇上一个男人  开始总是这样
"Mister, I met a man once when I was a kid," they'd always begin.
我猜我们的故事都不怎么有趣
I guess neither one of our stories is very funny.
告诉我
Tell me...
你是为了谁离开我?
...who was it you left me for?
是拉斯路 还是中间还有别的人
Was it Laszlo, or were there others in between...
或者你是不会说出来的人
...or aren't you the kind that tells?
(雷诺队长，警察首长)
我极端怀疑尤佳迪先生 把过境信函留下给宾勒先生了
I strongly suspect that Ugarte left the letters of transit with Mr. Blaine.
我建议立刻彻底搜查咖啡馆
I would suggest you search the cafe immediately.
如果信函在瑞克手上 他那么聪明你不可能找到的
If Rick has the letters, he's too smart to let you find them there.
你太夸奖他的聪明
You give him credit for too much cleverness.
我的印象他不过是另一个 莽撞的美国人
My impression was he's just another blundering American.
你不要低估美国人的莽撞
We mustrt underestimate American blundering.
1918年 当他们莽撞进入柏林时
I was with them when they blundered into Berlin in 1918.
我跟他们在一起呢 至于拉斯路 我要派人24小时监视
As to Laszlo, we want him watched 24 hours a day.
你可能会感兴趣想知道 此刻他正在来这里的途中
It may interest you to know that at this very moment he's on his way here.
我们没办法
There is nothing we can do.
很高兴看到你们  你们有充分休息吗 ?
I'm delighted to see you. Did you have a good night's rest?
我睡得很好
I slept very well.
奇怪  在卡萨布兰卡 不应该有人会睡得好的
Strange. Nobody's supposed to sleep well in Casablanca.
我们可否进行正事?  非常乐意  请坐下 谢谢
- May we proceed with the business? - With pleasure. Wort you sit down?
好吧  我们坦白说好了 你是第三帝国的逃犯
Laszlo, we will not mince words. You're an escaped prisoner of the Reich.
到目前为止你成功躲过我们
So far you have been fortunate in eluding us.
你抵达了卡萨布兰卡
You have reached Casablanca.
我有责任确保 你留在卡萨布兰卡
It is my duty to see that you stay in Casablanca.
你是否会成功当然仍是问题 一点也没
Whether or not you will succeed is problematic.
每张出境许可 都需雷诺队长签名
Not at all. Renault 's signature is necessary on every visa.
队长  你认为拉斯路 可能获得出境证吗
Captain, is it possible that Laszlo will receive a visa?
我恐怕不会 我表示抱歉  先生
I'm afraid not. My regrets, monsieur.
或许我会喜欢留在卡萨布兰卡
Well, perhaps I shall like it in Casablanca.
那小姐呢?
And mademoiselle?
你不必为我操心  你们想告诉我们的就是这些
- You needrt be concerned about me. - Is that all you wish to tell us?
别急  你的时间多的是
Don't be in such a hurry. You have all the time in the world.
你可能无限期留在卡萨布兰卡
You may be in Casablanca indefinitely.
或许你可能明天前往里斯本
Or you may leave for Lisbon tomorrow.
在一个条件之下 是什么?
- On one condition. - And that is?
你知道各地地下组织首领是谁 在巴黎  布拉格
You know the leader of the underground movement in Paris, in Prague...
布鲁赛尔  阿姆斯特丹
...Brussels, Amsterdam...
奥斯陆 贝尔格勒  雅典
...Oslo, Belgrade, Athens...
甚至在柏林 对  甚至在柏林
- Even Berlin. - Yes, even in Berlin.
如果你提供我他们的名字 和确实的行踪
If you will furnish me with their names and whereabouts...
你便可以在早上得到出境签证
...you'll have your visa in the morning.
并且分享 为第三帝国服务的荣誉
And the honor of having served the Third Reich.
我在德国集中营待过一年
I was in a German concentration camp for a year.
那份荣誉够享用一辈子了 你会给我们那些名字吗?
- That's honor enough for a lifetime. - You will give us the names?
如果在集中营时我没有给你们
If I didn't give them to you in a concentration camp...
在那儿 你能随意用更有说服力的方法
...where you had more persuasive methods at your disposal...
现在我当然不会给你了
...I certainly won't give them to you now.
如果你查获这些杀了他们呢?
And what if you track down these men and kill them?
如果你谋杀我们全部又怎样?
What if you murdered all of us?
在欧洲的每个角落 有上千人会崛起 取代我们的位置
From every corner of Europe, hundreds, thousands would rise to take our places.
即使纳粹党也不能杀得完
Even Nazis can't kill that fast.
拉斯路  你以能言善辩著称
Herr Laszlo, you have a reputation for eloquence which I can now understand.
我现在体会到 不过有点你说错
But in one aspect you are mistaken.
你说第三帝国所有的敌人都可以取代
You said the enemies of the Reich could all be replaced.
不过有一个例外
But there is one exception.
没有人能取代你的位置
No one could take your place ...
或防止在你逃走时发生的不幸
if anything unfortunate should occur to you while you were trying to escape.
你不敢在这里阻挡我
You won't dare to interfere with me here.
这里仍然是未被占领的法国
This is still unoccupied France.
任何违法的举动 都会影响雷诺队长的声誉
Any violation of neutrality would reflect on Captain Renault.
目前为止仍然在我控制之下 谢谢 对了  先生
- Monsieur, insofar as it is in my power. - Thank you.
昨晚你表示 对尤佳迪先生感兴趣
By the way, monsieur, last night you evinced an interest in Signor Ugarte.
我相信你有口信传给他
I believe you have a message for him?
没有什么重要的事 不过我现在可以跟他谈话吗?
Nothing important. But may I speak to him now?
你会发现谈话是单向的
You would find the conversation a trifle one-sided.
尤佳迪先生死了
Signor Ugarte is dead.
我正在写报告
I'm making out the report now.
我们还没决定他到底是自杀
We haven't quite decided whether he committed suicide...
或者企图逃走时死去
...or died trying to escape.
你们问完我们了吗?  暂时是的
- Are you quite finished with us? - For the time being.
日安
Good day.
毫无疑问他们下一步是找黑市
Undoubtedly, their next step will be to the black market.
对不起  队长
Excuse me, captain.
出现了另一件签证问题
Another visa problem has come up.
带她进来 是的
- Show her in. - Yes, sir.
对不起  先生 我们应付不了警察
Sorry, monsieur, we were never to handle the police.
这件事找法拉利先生才对  法拉利
- This is a job for Signor Ferrari. - Ferrari?
认识法拉利会很有帮助
It can be most helpful to know Signor Ferrari.
他独占了这里的黑市买卖
He pretty near has a monopoly on the black market here.
你在那边的蓝鹦鹉可以找到他
You will find him at the Blue Parrot.
谢谢
Thanks.
不要太灰心
Don't be too downearted.
或许你可以与雷诺队长 取得协议
Perhaps you can come to terms with Renault.
谢谢  先生 哈罗  法拉利
Thank you very much, signor.
早  瑞克
- Hello, Ferrari. - Good morning, Rick.
我看到巴士到了 我把我买的货一起带走
The bus is in. I'll take my shipment with me.
别急  我会叫人送去
I'll have it sent over. Have a drink with me.
跟我喝一杯吧 早上我不喝酒的
I never drink in the morning.
每次你送来给我的货 都短少了一点
And every time you send my shipment over it's a little short.
搬运费  我的孩子
Carrying charges, my boy. Carrying charges.
来  坐下
Here, sit down.
反正我有些事情跟你谈
There is something I want to talk over with you, anyhow.
"波旁" 威士忌
Bourbon.
尤佳迪的新闻使我很不舒服
The news about Ugarte upsets me very much.
你是个肥肿的虚伪者 尤佳迪的死你不会比我难过多少
You're a fat hypocrite. You don't feel any sorrier for Ugarte than I do.
当然不 我难过的是尤佳迪死了
Of course not. What upsets me is that Ugarte is dead...
没有人知道那过境信在那里
...and no one knows where those letters are.
几乎没有人
Practically no one.
如果我得到 肯定可以赚一大笔
If I had those letters, I could make a fortune.
我也可以 我是个贫穷的生意人
So could I, and I' m a poor businessman.
不管在谁手上我给他一个建议
I have a proposition for whoever has those letters.
我来安排交易
I'll handle the entire transaction.
承担一切风险把信卖出
Get rid of the letters, take all the risk, for a small percentage.
抽少部分利润 以及搬运费?
And the carrying charges?
自然会有一些意外支出
Naturally there will be a few incidental expenses.
这是我对持有信函的人提议
That's my proposition for whoever has those letters.
他出现时我会告诉他
I'll tell him when he comes in.
我开门见山跟你说 我认为你知道那些信在那里
Rick, I think you know where those letters are.
你有伴了 雷诺和史查沙大概也这样想
You're in good company. Renault and Strasser probably think so too.
所以我才到这里 给他们机会搜索我的店
That's why I came here. To give them a chance to ransack my place.
别傻了  跟我说实话 你需要一个合伙人
Rick, don't be a fool. Take me into your confidence. You need a partner.
失陪  我要回去了
Excuse me, I' II be getting back.
早 法拉利先生是那边桌子的肥仔
- Morning. - Signor Ferrari is the fat gent at the table.
在全摩洛哥 你也找不到这么珍贵的东西
You will not find a treasure like this in all Morocco.
小姐  只要七百法O
Only 700 francs.
你被骗了 没关系  谢谢
- You're being cheated. - Doesrt matter, thank you.
女士是瑞克的朋友 瑞克的朋友我们给一点折扣
For friends of Rick's we have a small discount.
我刚才说七百法O吗?  两百法O卖给你
Did I say 700 francs? You can have it for 200.
对不起  昨晚你来拜访时 我正处于不适合待客的状态
I'm sorry I was in no condition to receive you when you called on me last night.
没关系 瑞克的特别朋友
Doesrt matter.
我们有特别的折扣  一百法O
For special friends of Rick's we have a special discount. 100 francs.
那故事把我弄糊涂了 或者是喝多了"波旁" 吧
Your story had me a little confused. Or maybe it was the bourbon.
我有些桌巾  一些餐巾
I have some tablecloths, napkins...
谢谢  我真的不感兴趣  请等一会儿
- Thank you. I' m really not interested. - Please, one minute.
为什么你要回来呢?
Why did you come back?
为了告诉我你为何叫我在火车站白等  -对
To tell me why you ran out on me at the railway station? -Yes.
你现在可以告诉我 我比较清醒了
Well, you can tell me now. I'm reasonably sober.
我想我不会说了  瑞克
I don't think I will, Rick.
为何不 我买了火车票进退两难
Why not? After all, I got stuck with a railway ticket.
我想我有权利知道
I think I' m entitled to know.
昨晚我看到在你身上 发生了什么
Last night I saw what has happened to you.
在巴黎的瑞克  我可以告诉他 他能够明白
The Rick I knew in Paris, I could tell him, he'd understand.
可是用那种怨恨眼光看我的人
But the one who looked at me with such hatred...
我很快会离开卡萨兰加 我们永远不会再见面了
I'll be leaving Casablanca soon. We'll never see each other again.
我们在巴黎相爱的时候 我们彼此了解并不多
We knew very little about each other when we were in love in Paris.
如果我们维持那样
If we leave it that way,
或许我们会记住那些日子 而不是卡萨布兰卡
maybe we'll remember those days and not Casablanca.
不是昨晚
Not last night.
你舍我而去  因为你知道将会是什么样子
Did you run out on me because you knew what it would be like?
逃避警察  无时无刻不在逃亡
Hiding from the police, running away all the time?
如果你要相信是那样随便你
You can believe that if you want to.
我已不再逃亡了 我安定下来了
Well, I' m not running away anymore. I'm settled now.
虽然是酒馆  不过是事实
Above a saloon, it's true...
要上飞机的话
...but walk up a flight...
我会算你一份
...I' II be expecting you.
都一样 有一天你会对拉斯路撒谎
All the same, someday you'll lie to Laszlo.
你会去的
You'll be there.
不  瑞克
No, Rick.
不  维多拉斯路是我的丈夫
No. You see, Victor Laszlo is my husband.
以前也是 甚至我在巴黎认识你之前也是
And was, even when I knew you in Paris.
我刚才正跟拉斯路先生说  很不幸我无法帮助你们
I was just telling Monsieur Laszlo that unfortunately I' m not able to help him.
是这样的  亲爱的 话已传开了
You see, my dear, word has gone around.
身为卡萨布兰卡 所有非法活动的领导人
As leader of all illegal activities in Casablanca,
我是个有影响力和受尊重的人
I am influential and respected
替拉斯路先生做任何事 要冒生命危险并不值得
But it would not be won'th my life to do anything for Monsieur Laszlo.
不过你  却是另一回事
You, however, are a different matter.
法拉利先生认为有可能 替你拿到一份签证
Signor Ferrari thinks it might just be possible to get an exit visa for you.
你是说让我单独离开 只能单独一人
- You mean for me to go on alone? - And only alone.
我会留在这里继续想办法 我肯定再过一阵子...
I'll stay here and keep on trying. I'm sure in a little while...
我还是坦白一点好  先生
Might as well be frank, monsieur.
需要奇迹 你才可能离开卡萨布兰卡
It would take a miracle to get you out.
德国人是剥夺奇迹的歹徒
The Germans have outlawed miracles.
我们只对两位签证感兴趣 先生
We are only interested in two visas.
拜托  伊莎  不要急躁 不  维多  不
- Please, llsa, don't be hasty. - No, Victor.
你们两位会想讨论这件事
You two will want to discuss this.
失陪  我会在酒吧
Excuse me. I' II be at the bar.
不  伊莎 我不能让你留在这里
No, llsa. I won't let you stay here.
你必须到美国去 我相信我终会逃出  跟你会合
You must get to America. Believe me, somehow I will get out and join you.
维多  情况不一样
But if the situation were different...
如果我必须留下 只有一份签证
...if I had to stay and there were only visa for one...
你会要吗?
...would you take it?
对  我会
Yes, I would.
对  我明白
Yes, I see.
当要离开"流尔"  我遇上麻烦时
When I had trouble getting out of Lille,
你为什么不把我留在那儿?
why didn't you leave me there?
当我在马赛生病时 耽搁你两个星期
When I was sick in Marseilles for two weeks...
你无时无刻不冒着生命危险
...and you were in danger every minute...
那时候你为什么不留下我?
...why didn't you leave me then?
我本来要 总是有些东西阻止我
I meant to, but something always held me up.
我非常爱你  伊莎
Ilove you very much, llsa.
我会保守你的秘密
Your secret will be safe with me.
法拉利在等我们的答案
Ferrari is waiting for our answer.
不能超过五十法O
Not more than 50 francs.
我们已经决定了  法拉利先生
We've decided, Signor Ferrari.
从现在起我们只寻求两份签证 非常感谢你
For the present we will go on looking for two visas. Thank you very much.
祝你好运  务必小心
Well, good luck, but be careful.
你知道你被跟踪吗?  当然  已经习以为常
- You know you're being shadowed? - Of course. It becomes an instinct.
我发现在某方面来说 你是个幸运的人  先生
I observe that you, in one respect, are a very fortunate man.
我觉得想再给你一个建议 为了什么我也不知道
I am moved to make one more suggestion. Why, I do not know.
因为你不可能给我好处
Because it cannot possibly profit me.
你有听闻尤佳迪先生 和过境信吗?
Have you heard about Ugarte and the letters of transit?
是  一点点
Yes, something.
他们逮捕尤佳迪时 没有在他身上找到那些信
Those letters were not found on Ugarte when they arrested him.
你知道信在那里吗?
- You know where they are? - Not for sure.
不过我猜尤佳迪 把信留给瑞克先生
But I'd guess that Ugarte left those letters with Monsieur Rick.
那瑞克有难以理解的习惯
A difficult customer, that Rick.
没有人知道 他会做什么及为什么
One never knows what he'll do or why.
不过值得试一试
But it is won'th a chance.
非常感谢你  日安
Thank you very much. Good day.
再见  谢谢你的咖啡  先生
Goodbye. Thank you for your coffee.
我们离开卡萨布兰卡后 我将会怀念那咖啡
I shall miss that when we leave Casablanca.
请你跟我分享 日安  小姐
Gracious of you to share it with me. Good day, mademoiselle.
先生 日安
- Monsieur. - Good day.
敬你  先生 祝好运
- Here's to you, sir. - Good luck.
我要走了  请给我帐单
- I'd better be going. - My check, please.
我必须警告你  这是个危险的地方  很多贪心的人
I have to warn you, sir. This is a dangerous place. Full of vultures.
到处是贪心的人 谢谢 再见  先生
- Vultures everywhere. Thanks for everything. - Goodbye.
很荣幸认识你
It has been a pleasure to meet you.
对不起
I'm sorry.
瑞克先生 你快成为自己最好的顾客了
Monsieur Rick, you are getting to be your best customer.
在喝酒?  你使我很高兴
Well, drinking. I'm very pleased with you.
你现在开始 像法国人那样生活了
You're beginning to live like a Frenchman.
你的手下今天下午 来搅乱我的店
That was some going-over your men gave my place.
我们差点来不及清理开门营业
We barely got cleaned up in time to open.
我告诉过史查沙休不会在这里 找到那些信
I told Strasser he wouldn't find the letters here.
不过我告诉我的手下 要格外有破坏力  你知道
But I told my men to be especially destructive.
那可叫德国人刮目相看
You know how that impresses Germans.
瑞克  你有那些过境信吗?
Rick, have you got those letters of transit?
你是倾向亲德还是自由法国?
Louis, are you Pro-Vichy or Free French?
我活该  问这直接的问题 这话题结束
Serves me right for asking a direct question. The subject is closed.
似乎你晚了一步
It looks like you're a little late.
原来伊娃向敌人投诚了
So Yvonne's gone over to the enemy.
谁知道  以她自己的方法 她可能组织第二条前线
Who knows? In her own way, she may constitute an entire second front.
我想我该去 奉承一下史查沙少校 回头见!  瑞克
I think it's time for me to flatter Strasser a little. I' II see you later.
沙克!
Sascha!
法国七十五
French 75s.
我们要一整排  沙克 从这里开始  到这里结束
Put up a whole row of them, Sascha. Starting here and ending here.
我们从两杯开始
We will begin with two.
你不是法国人吗？ (法语)
竟然跟这种德国人约会 关你什么事
你说什么?  麻烦你再说一次
What did you say? Would you kindly repeat it?
我说什么与你无关 我会使它变成跟我有关
- What I said is none of your business. - I' II make it my business.
停手!求求你，求求你停手
我不喜欢人家在我的店乱来 不抛开政治就滚出去
I don't like disturbances in my place. Either lay off politics or get out.
有一天，你会得到报应的
你看到了吧  队长
You see, captain?
情况并不如你想像的那么稳定
The situation is not as under control as you believe.
亲爱的少校 我们正尽量跟贵政府合作
We try to cooperate with your government.
我们无法规定人民的感受
But we cannot regulate the feelings of our people.
队长 你完全肯定你帮那一边吗
Captain, are you certain which side you're on?
我没有信念 如果你指这一方面
I have no conviction, if that's what you mean.
我看风转舵  目前的风向
I blow with the wind...
正巧从维琪(亲德)吹来
...and the prevailing wind happens to be from Vichy.
如果风向改了呢?
And if it should change?
我肯定 帝国不会承认那种可能性
Surely the Reich doesn't admit that possibility?
我们关心的不只是卡萨布兰卡
We are concerned about more than Casablanca.
我们知道 每个在非洲的法国管区
We know that every French province in Africa is honeycombed with traitors.
都布满了叛徒  正在等候机会 或许在等候一位领导人
Waiting for their chance. Waiting perhaps for a leader.
领导人?  像拉斯路?
Aleader? Like Laszlo?
我一直在想
I have been thinking.
让他离开太危险 但让他留下也可能太危险
It's too dangerous to let him go, it may be too dangerous to let him stay.
我明白你的意思
I see what you mean.
(德语)
谢谢  卡尔 你的  太太
Thank you, Carl.
谢谢  卡尔
卡尔  坐下 跟我们喝杯白兰地
Sit down. Have a brandy with us.
庆祝我们明天到美国去
To celebrate our leaving for America tomorrow.
非常谢谢
Thank you very much.
我早想到你会请我喝 所以我拿了上等的白兰地
I thought you would ask me, so I brought the good brandy...
还有...高脚杯
...and a third glass.
终于  这一天到来了
At last the day's came!
从现在起我们只说英文
Frau Leuchtag and I are speaking nothing but English now.
这样我们到美国后 会感觉像回到家一样
So we should feel at home when we get to America.
很不错的主意
A very nice idea.
为美国喝一杯
To America.
亲爱的  什么表(几点了)?
What watch?
十个表(十点) 那么多(这么晚了)
- Ten watch. - Such much?
你们会在美国过得非常愉快
You will get along beautifully in America.
幸运女神有没有照顾你?
How is lady luck treating you?
真可惜
Oh, too bad.
他就在那边
You'll find him over there.
瑞克先生 是
- Monsieur Rick? - Yes?
我可否跟你说几句话  你怎么进来的?  你还未成年
- Could I speak to you, please? - How'd you get in here? You're underage.
我跟雷诺队长一起来的 我早该猜到
- I came with Captain Renault. - I should have known.
我的丈夫也跟我一起
My husband is with me too.
是吗?  雷诺队长思想越来开明
He is? Captain Renault 's getting broad-minded. Sit down.
坐下  要喝一杯吗?
Have a drink?
当然不喝  你介意我喝吗?  不
No, of course not. You mind if I do?
瑞克先生
Monsieur Rick...
雷诺队长是怎样的人?  就像其他的男人  或者更像
...what kind of a man is Captain Renault? - Like any other man, only more so.
我是说
No, I mean...
他值得信任吗?  他的话...
...is he trustwon'thy? Is his word...?
等一下  谁叫你来问我的?  他叫我的  雷诺队长
- Just a minute. Who told you to ask me that? - He did. Captain Renault did.
我也猜到  你的丈夫呢?
I thought so. Where's your husband?
在轮盘桌那边 想要赢足够的钱 买我们的出境证
At the roulette table, trying to win enough for our exit visas.
当然他正在输钱
Oh, of course he's losing.
你们结婚多久了?  八个星期
- How long have you been married? - Eight weeks.
我们从保加利亚来
We come from Bulgaria.
那里的情况非常坏  先生
Things are very bad there.
魔鬼押着人民的脖子
The devil has the people by the throat.
所以犹安和我  我们...
So Jan and I, we...
我们不想子女在那种地方长大
We do not want our children to grow up in such a country.
所以你们决定去美国
- So you decided to go to America. - Yes.
对  可是我们钱不多
But we haven't much money...
旅费那么贵而且困难
...and traveling is so expensive and difficult.
来这里的花费 比我们预算高很多
It was much more than we thought to get here.
然后雷诺队长看到我们
And then Captain Renault sees us...
他很仁慈  他想帮我们 对  我打赌是
...and he is so kind, he wants to help us. - Yes, I' II bet.
他告诉我 他可以给我们出境签证
He tells me he can give us an exit visa.
可是  我们没有钱
But we have no money.
他知道吗?  知道
- Does he know that? - Yes.
那他仍然愿意给你签证
- And he's still willing to give you a visa? - Yes.
对  先生 而你想知道... 他会不会遵守诺言?
- And you want to know...? - Will he keep his word?
他一直都有
He always has.
先生  你是一个男人
You are a man.
假设有一个人非常爱你
If someone loved you very much...
她只求能给你快乐
...so that your happiness was the only thing that she wanted in the world...
为了肯定能办到 她做了件坏事
...and she did a bad thing to make certain of it...
你会不会原谅她?  没有人曾经那么爱我
...could you forgive her? - Nobody ever loved me that much.
他一直都不知道 那女孩把做过的坏事藏在心里
And he never knew, and the girl kept this bad thing locked in her heart...
这样不会有关系吧  会不会?
...that would be all right, wouldn't it?
你要我提意见吗?  是  拜托
- You want my advice? - Yes, please.
回到保加利亚去
Go back to Bulgaria.
如果你知道能离开欧洲到美国 对我们有多重要
Oh, but if you knew what it means to us to leave Europe, to get to America...
如果犹安发现了 他那么孩子气
Oh, but if Jan should find out. He is such a boy.
在很多方面  我比他成熟 对
In many ways I am so much older than he is.
在卡萨布兰卡每个人都有困难
Yes, well, everybody in Casablanca has problems.
你的困难可能会解决的  失陪 谢谢  先生
- Yours may work out. You'll excuse me. - Thank you, monsieur.
晚安
- Good evening. - Good evening.
你看  我们又来了 我认为那是对山姆的恭维
- You see? Here we are again. - I take that as a great compliment to Sam.
我猜对你而言他代表巴黎 那些较快乐的日子
I suppose he means to you Paris of happier days.
的确是 我们可否选择靠近他的桌子
He does. Could we have a table close to him?
并且离史查沙少校越远越好
And as far away from Major Strasser as possible.
这样的安排可能有点困难
The geography may be a little difficult to arrange.
保罗  三十号桌
- Paul, table 30. - Yes, sir.
是的  先生  请往这边
Right this way, if you please.
我叫山姆弹"时光飞逝"  我相信那是你偏爱的曲子
I'll have Sam play "As Time Goes By." I believe that's your favorite tune.
谢谢
Thank you.
两杯干邑(白兰地)麻烦你 干邑
- Two cognacs, please. - Cognac.
下注，先生女士
赌博游戏继续进行
先生女士，下注
游戏继续，下注
你要不要再下注呢?  先生
Do you wish to place another bet, sir?
不  不  我想不要了
No. No, I guess not.
你今晚买过22号吗?
Have you tried 22 tonight?
我说22
I said 22.
下注，先生女士，游戏继续
留在那里
Leave it there.
下注，先生女士 游戏继续进行
好了，不要下注 二十二
拿去兑现金  不要再回来
Cash it in and don't come back.
你肯定这地方诚实吗?
Are you sure this place is honest?
诚实?  日子有多长就有多诚实
Honest? As honest as the day is long.
不要再下注了
我们今天成绩如何?
How are we doing tonight?
比我预料的少了几千块
A couple of thousand less than I thought there would be.
瑞克先生...我...
Monsieur Rick...
他走运而已
He's just a lucky guy.
瑞克先生 我倒杯咖啡给你好吗
Monsieur Rick, may I get you a cup of coffee?
不  谢谢  卡尔 瑞克先生
- No, thanks, Carl. - Monsieur Rick...
雷诺队长  我可否...
Captain Renault, may l- -?
在这里不行 明早到我办公室 我们依照手续
Not here. Come to my office in the morning. We'll do everything businesslike.
我们会在六点到
- We'll be there at 6.
我会在十点到  我很替你们高兴
- I'll be there at 10. I'm very happy for both of you.
你赢钱有一点奇怪
Still, it's very strange that you won.
或许不是那么奇怪
Well, maybe not so strange.
明天早上见 非常谢谢  雷诺队长
- I'll see you in the morning. - Thank you, Captain Renault.
不  是真的吗?
No!
老板  你做了一件天大的好事
Boss, you've done a beautiful thing.
走开  疯狂的俄国人
Go away, you crazy Russian.
正如我怀疑 你是不折不扣的感情用事者  为什么?
- As I suspected. You're a rank sentimentalist. - Yeah? Why?
为什么你干扰我小小的罗曼史
Why do you interfere with my little romances?
就算是向爱情致敬吧
Put it down as a gesture to love.
这一次我原谅你
Well, I' II forgive you this time.
不过明天晚上我会带来  一位令窒息的金发美女
But I' II be in tomorrow night with a breathtaking blond.
如果她输钱会叫我非常高兴
And it'll make me very happy if she loses.
宾勒先生 不晓得可否跟你谈谈
- Mr. Blaine, I wonder if I could talk to you. - Go ahead.
说吧 有别的说话地方吗?
Well, isn't there some other place?
我要说的是颇机密的事
It's rather confidential, what I have to say.
在我办公室 好的
- In my office. - Right.
你一定知道离开卡萨布兰卡 对我很重要
You must know it's very important I get out of Casablanca.
身为这伟大运动的领导人之一 是一份莫大的荣幸
It's my privilege to be one of the leaders of a great movement.
你知道我一直从事什么
You know what I' ve been doing.
你知道那有多重要  对全世界 对千百万人的生命
You know what it means to the work, to the lives of thousands of people...
如果我能到美国继续我的工作
...that I reach America and continue my work.
我对政治不感兴趣
I'm not interested in politics.
世界的问题不是我分内的事
The problems of the world are not in my department.
我是开酒馆的
I'm a saloonkeeper.
我从事地下工作的朋友告诉我  你有不平凡的纪录
My friends in the underground tell me that you have quite a record.
你运枪械到衣索比亚
You ran guns to Ethiopia.
你在西班牙对抗法西斯 那又怎样?
- You fought against the fascists in Spain. - What of it?
你总是帮受迫害的那边打仗  不是有点奇怪吗?
Isn't it strange you're always fighting on the side of the underdog?
对 我并发现那是种昂贵的喜好
Yes, I found that a very expensive hobby.
不过我那时候不太会做生意
But then I never was much of a businessman.
现在你是否较会做生意 晓得...  十万法O这价码
Are you enough of a businessman to appreciate an offer of 100,000 francs?
我欣赏  可是我不接受 我加到二十万
- I appreciate it, but I don't accept it. - 200,000.
朋友 你可以加到一百万或三百万
My friend, you could make it a million francs or three.
我的答案仍然一样
My answer would still be the same.
一定有原因使你不愿意给我
There must be some reason why you won't let me.
是有
There is.
我建议你去问你的妻子
I suggest that you ask your wife.
你说什么?  我说问你的妻子
- I beg your pardon? - I said, ask your wife.
我的妻子 对
- My wife? - Yes.
(德国歌)
弹奏"马赛曲"  快
Play "La Marseillaise." Play it!
法国万岁，民主万岁
你明白我的意思了吧 如果在咖啡馆出现的拉斯路
See what I mean? If Laszlo 's presence in a cafe...
可以鼓动这样不幸的示威行动
...can inspire this demonstration...
他在卡萨布兰卡 还会导致什么?
...what more will his presence in Casablanca bring on?
我奉劝把这地方马上查封
I advise that this place be shut up at once.
可是大家都那么开心
- But everybody's having a good time.
对  太开心了 这地方必须查封
- Yes, much too good a time. The place is to be closed.
可是我没有藉口查封  找一个
- But I have no excuse to close it. - Find one.
祝健康!先生 健康
所有人必须马上离开
Everybody is to leave immediately.
这咖啡馆关闭 直到另行通知为止
This cafe is closed until further notice.
马上清场
Clear the room at once.
你怎么可以查封我 有什么理由
How can you close me up?
我很震惊  发现这里进行赌博
I'm shocked, shocked to find that gambling is going on in here.
你赢的钱  先生  很谢谢你
- Your winnings, sir. - Thank you.
所有人马上出去
Everybody out at once.
经过这次骚动后
After this disturbance...
拉斯路先生留在卡萨布兰卡已不再安全了
...it is not safe for Laszlo to stay in Casablanca.
今早你暗示他离开卡萨布兰卡  并不安全
This morning you implied it wasrt safe to leave Casablanca.
不错  除了一处目的地 回到被占领的法国
That is also true, except for one destination: Occupied France.
被占领的法国?
- Occupied France? - Under safe conduct from me.
在我的安全保证下 一文不值
Of what value is that?
你可能记得过去德国的信誉 值多少钱吧!
You may recall what German guarantees have been won'th in the past.
你只有两个选择 是什么?
- There are two other alternatives for him. - What are they?
有可能法国当局会找一个理由
The French authorities may find a reason...
把他送进这儿的集中营
...to put him in the concentration camp here.
另一个选择呢?
The other alternative?
亲爱的小姐  或许你已经察觉
My dear, perhaps you have already observed...
在卡萨布兰卡人命不值钱
...that in Casablanca human life is cheap.
晚安  小姐
Good night, mademoiselle.
瑞克怎么回事?  我们待会儿再商量
- What happened with Rick? - We'll discuss it later.
我们忠心的朋友仍然在那里
Our faithful friend is still there.
维多 求你今晚不要去地下会议
Please don't go to the underground meeting tonight.
我一定要去
I must.
况且一个男人能在他妻子面前 扮演英雄的机会不多
Besides, it isn't often that a man gets to display heroics before his wife.
不要开玩笑 经过史查沙少校今晚的警告后
Don't joke. After Major Strasser's warning tonight, I' m frightened.
我很害怕 告诉你事实  我也害怕
Tell you the truth, I'm frightened too.
我应该留在这里?  躲在饭店房间
Shall I remain here in a hotel room, hiding?
或者我应该继续尽力而为?
Or shall I carry on the best I can?
不管我说什么你也会继续做
Whatever I' d say, you would carry on.
维多 为何你不告诉我瑞克的事 你发现了什么?
Victor, why don't you tell me about Rick? What did you find out?
很明显那些信在他手上
- Apparently he has the letters. - Yes?
还有呢?  可是没有要卖的意思
But no intention of selling them.
一般人会以为情感不能打动他 钱应该可以
You'd think if sentiment wouldn't persuade him, money would.
他有没有跟你说理由是什么?
Did he give any reason?
他建议我问你  问我?
- He suggested I ask you. - Ask me?
对  他说: 问你的妻子
Yes, he said, "Ask your wife."
我不知道他为什么那样说
I don't know why he said that.
我们外头那位朋友 现在应该以为我们休息了
Well, our friend outside will think we've retired by now.
我待会儿就去
I'll be going in a few minutes.
伊莎  我... 什么?
- Ilsa, I... - Yes?
我在集中营的时候
When I was in the concentration camp...
你在巴黎寂寞吗?
...were you lonely in Paris?
对  维多  我是寂寞
Yes, Victor, I was.
我知道寂寞是什么样子
I know how it is to be lonely.
有什么事你想要告诉我的吗?
Is there anything you wish to tell me?
没有  维多
No, Victor, there isn't.
我非常爱你  亲爱的
Ilove you very much, my dear.
是  是  我知道
Yes, I know.
维多  不管我做什么 你会不会相信我...
Victor, whatever I do, will you believe that I...?
你甚至不必说出来
You don't even have to say it.
我也相信你
I'll believe.
晚安  亲爱的
Good night, dear.
晚安
Good night.
维多 什么事?  亲爱的
- Victor. - Yes, dear?
要小心
Be careful.
当然  我会小心
Of course I' II be careful.
你的情况非常好  瑞克先生
Well, you are in pretty good shape, Herr Rick.
我可以支持多久不营业
How long can I afford to stay closed?
两星期或者三星期
Two weeks, maybe three.
或者我不必关门 以前用贿赂有效
Maybe I won't have to. A bribe has worked before.
目前所有人依旧发薪水
In the meantime, everybody stays on salary.
谢谢  瑞克先生
Thank you, Herr Rick.
沙克听到一定很高兴 我欠他钱
Sascha will be happy to hear it. I owe him money.
你把门锁好  可以吗?  卡尔
- You finish locking up, will you, Carl - I will.
我会的 然后我要去开会... 别告诉我你去那里
- Then I am going to the meeting... - Don't tell me where you're going.
我不会
I won't.
晚安
Good night.
晚安  瑞克先生
Good night, Mr. Rick.
你怎么进来的?  街外的楼梯
- How did you get in? - The stairs from the street.
今天早上我跟你说有空来坐
I told you this morning you'd come around,
不过这似乎比预定的稍早了点
but this is ahead of schedule.
你不坐下来吗?
Well, won't you sit down?
理查  我必须见你 再度叫理查  我们回到巴黎了
- Richard, I had to see you. - "Richard" again. We're back in Paris.
求求你
Please.
你的突然来访是否有可能 跟那些过境信有关呢?
Your visit isn't connected by any chance with the letters of transit?
似乎只要信一天还在我手上  我就不愁寂寞了
Seems as long as I have those letters I'll never be lonely.
你要多少钱都可以  不过你一定要把那些信给我
Ask any price you want, but you must give me the letters.
我已经跟你的丈夫讲清楚了  绝不交易
I went all through that with your husband. It 's no deal.
我知道你对我的感受 可是我得要求你为更重要的事
I know how you feel about me...
先将自己的感受抛在一边
...but put your feelings aside for something more important.
我又要再听一次 你丈夫有多伟大
I have to hear again what a great man your husband is...
他为多么重要的目标战斗吗?
...what an important cause he's fighting for?
那也是你的目标
It was your cause too.
以你自己的方式 你也为相同的目标战斗
In your own way, you were fighting for the same thing.
我不再为任何事战斗了 除了为自己
I'm not fighting for anything anymore except myself.
我唯一感兴趣的目标是自己
I'm the only cause I' m interested in.
理查  我们曾经相爱过 如果那些日子对你有意义
We loved each other once. If those days meant anything at all to you...
如果我是你就不会提起巴黎 那是差劲的推销把戏
I wouldn't bring up Paris if I were you. It's poor salesmanship.
求求你听我说 如果你知道事实是怎么回事
Listen to me. If you knew what really happened,
如果你知道事情的真相 不管你说什么我也不会相信
if you only knew the truth. I wouldn't believe you no matter what you said.
为了达到目的 你现在什么也说得出口
You'd say anything now to get what you want.
你很遗撼  是吗?
You want to feel sorry for yourself, don't you?
那么多事危在旦夕 你想到的只有自己的感觉
With so much at stake all you can think of is your feelings.
一个女人伤害了你 你便对全世界报复
One woman has hurt you, and you take your revenge on the rest of the world.
你是...个胆小鬼  弱者...
You're a coward and a weakling.
不  不  理查  对不起
No. Oh, Richard. I' m sorry.
对不起  可是... 可是你是我们最后的希望
I'm sorry, but you are our last hope.
如果你不帮我们 维多拉斯路会死在卡萨布兰卡
If you don't help us, Victor Laszlo will die in Casablanca.
那又怎样?
What of it?
我也会死在卡萨布兰卡 这是死亡的好地方
I'm going to die in Casablanca. It's a good spot for it.
现在  如果你...
Now, if you'll...
好吧
All right.
我尝试跟你讲道理
I tried to reason with you.
我什么法子也试了 现在我要那些信
I tried everything. Now, I want those letters.
去拿给我  我不必去拿  就在这里
- Get them for me. - I don't have to. I got them right here.
放在桌上
Put them on the table.
不
No.
最后一次  放在桌上
For the last time, put them on the table.
如果拉斯路和他的目标对你那么重要 什么也挡不住你
If Laszlo and the cause mean so much to you, you won't stop at anything.
好吧  我让你更方便一点
All right, I'll make it easier for you.
开枪吧  你将会帮了我一个忙
Go ahead and shoot. You'll be doing me a favor.
理查
Richard...
我尽量避开你
...I tried to stay away.
我以为我永远不会再见到你
I thought I would never see you again.
你已经在我生命中消失
That you were out of my life.
你离开巴黎的那天
The day you left Paris...
如果你知道我的感受
...if you knew what I went through.
如果你知道我多爱你
If you knew how much I loved you.
我仍然有多么爱你
How much I still love you.
然后呢?
And then?
我们结婚后不久维多回到捷克
It wasrt long after we were married that Victor went back to Czechoslovakia.
他们需要他在布拉格 可是秘密警察在等着他
They needed him in Prague, but there the Gestapo were waiting for him.
只看到报上的两行小启
Just a two-line item in the paper:
维多拉斯路被逮捕送往集中营
"Victor Laszlo apprehended. Sent to concentration camp."
我发狂一般 好几个月我努力打听消息
I was frantic. For months I tried to get word.
消息终于来了
Then it came.
他死了 逃走的时候被枪打死
He was dead. Shot trying to escape.
我好寂寞  我一无所有 连希望也没有
I was lonely. I had nothing, not even hope.
后来我遇上你
Then I met you.
为什么你不对我诚实说?  为什么你守着结婚的秘密?
Why werert you honest with me? Why did you keep your marriage a secret?
那不是我的秘密  理查 是维多要那样
It wasrt my secret, Richard. Victor wanted it that way.
甚至我们最要好的朋友 也不知道我们的婚事
Not even our closest friends knew about our marriage.
那是他保护我的方法  关于他的工作我知道太多了
That was his way of protecting me. I knew so much about his work.
如果秘密警察发现我是他妻子
If the Gestapo found out I was his wife it would be dangerous for me...
那会为我和地下工作者 带来危险
...and for those working with us.
你什么时候发现他仍然活着?
And when did you first find out he was alive?
刚好我们准备一起离开巴黎前
Just before you and I were to leave Paris together.
一个朋友前来告诉我维多活着
A friend came and told me that Victor was alive.
他们把他藏在巴黎市郊的 一节货运车厢上
They were hiding him in a freight car on the outskirts of Paris.
他生病需要我
He was sick. He needed me.
我想告诉你可是我不敢
I wanted to tell you, but I didn't dare.
我知道  你一定不会离开巴黎  秘密警察便会捉到你
I knew you wouldn't have left Paris, and the Gestapo would have caught you.
所以我...
Well...
其余的你已知道了
...well, you know the rest.
仍然是一个没有结局的故事
Well, it's still a story without an ending.
那现在呢?
What about now?
现在?
Now?
我不知道
I don't know.
我知道我再没有勇气离开你
I know that I' II never have the strength to leave you again.
那拉斯路呢?
And Laszlo?
你会帮助他的 理查  对不对?  你设法使他离境
You'll help him now, Richard, won't you? You'll see that he gets out.
他便能拥有他的工作 他生存的所有意义
Then he'll have his work. All that he's been living for.
除了一样
All except one.
他将没有你
He won't have you.
我无法再挣扎下去
I can't fight it anymore.
我曾舍你而去 第二次我做不到
I ran away from you once. I can't do it again.
我再也不知道 什么是对什么是错
Oh, I don't know what's right any longer.
你必须为我们两个想
You have to think for both of us.
为我们所有人想
For all of us.
好吧  我会的
All right. I will.
永志不忘
Here's looking at you, kid.
我希望我没有那么爱你
I wish I didn't love you so much.
我想我们甩掉他们了
- I think we lost them. - Yes.
对  我恐怕他们抓到其他的人 进里面去
- I' m afraid they caught some of the others. - Come inside.
来  拉斯路先生 我会立刻帮你
Come, Mr. Laszlo, I will help you immediately.
谢谢
Thank you.
卡尔  怎么回事?
Carl, what happened?
警察查获我们的会议 瑞克先生 我们刚好来得及逃走
The police break up our meeting, Herr Rick. We escaped at the last moment.
上来一下 好  我来
- Come up here a minute. - Yes, I come.
我要你把后门关掉 可能会引起警察的注意
Turn out the light in the rear entrance. It might attract the police.
沙克每天都会关的 今晚他忘记了
- But Sascha always puts out that light. - Tonight he forgot.
好  我来了  我会去关
Yes, I come. I will do it.
我要你送林小姐回家 好的
- I want you to take Miss Lund home. - Yes, sir.
没什么  只是小小的割伤 我们被迫从窗户爬出来
It's nothing, just a little cut. We had to get through a window.
这可能有帮助
This might come in handy.
谢谢
Thank you.
千钧一发?  对  挺危险
- Had a close one, eh? - Yes, rather.
你有时候会不会想这值得吗?
Don't you sometimes wonder if it's won'th all this?
我是指你战斗的目标
I mean, what you're fighting for.
我不如问为什么我们要呼吸
We might as well question why we breathe.
如果我们不呼吸  我们就会死
If we stop breathing, we'll die.
如果我们停止对抗敌人 世界就会死
If we stop fighting our enemies, the world will die.
又怎样?  苦难就结束了
What of it? Then it'll be out of its misery.
你知道你的口气像什么吗?
You know how you sound, Monsieur Blaine?
像一个拿内心不相信的事情
Like a man who's trying to convince himself of something...
来说服自己的人
...he doesn't believe in his heart.
我们每一个人都有一个目标 善意的  或邪恶的
Each of us has a destiny. For good, or for evil.
我明白了 我怀疑你是否真明白
- I get the point. - I wonder if you do.
我怀疑你知不知道 你在逃避自己
I wonder if you know that you're trying to escape from yourself...
你将永远不会成功
...and that you'll never succeed.
你似乎对我的目标t如指掌
You seem to know all about my destiny.
我知道关于你的事 比你怀疑的多
I know a good deal more about you than you suspect.
例如我知道你爱上一个女人
I know that you're in love with a woman.
或者这是一种奇怪的现象
It's perhaps a strange circumstance...
我们两个会爱着同一个女人
...that we both should be in love with the same woman.
我走进这咖啡馆的第一个晚上
The first evening I came into this cafe...
我知道 你和伊莎之间有些不寻常
...I knew there was something between you and llsa.
既然不能责怪任何人
Since no one is to blame...
我不要求解释 我只要求一件事
...I demand no explanation. I ask only one thing.
你不愿给我过境信函  没关系
You won't give me the letters of transit. All right.
不过我要我的妻子安全
But I want my wife to be safe.
我请求你帮忙
I ask you as a favor...
用那些信带她离开卡萨布兰卡
...to use the letters to take her away from Casablanca.
你那么爱她吗?
You love her that much?
或者你只把我想成 一个主义的领导者
Apparently you think of me only as the leader of a cause.
我也是个人
Well, I am also a human being.
对  我是那么爱她
Yes, I love her that much.
拉斯路先生 什么事?
- Monsieur Laszlo? - Yes?
你跟我们走 我们有你的逮捕令
You'll come with us. We have a warrant for your arrest.
什么罪名?
On what charge?
雷诺队长稍后会跟你讨论
Captain Renault will discuss that with you later.
似乎命运正在插手
It seems that destiny has taken a hand.
你没有实在的证据  你也知道
You haven't any proof, and you know it.
这里是未被占领的法国  不是德国
This isn't Germany or occupied France.
你能做的只是罚他几千法O 或者拘禁30天
All you can do is fine him and give him 30 days.
不如现在放他
You might as well let him go now.
瑞克  我奉劝你不要对 拉斯路发生的事太感兴趣
I'd advise you not to be too interested in what happens to Laszlo.
如果你企图帮他逃走
If you were to help him escape...
你为什么认为 我会为拉斯路冒险
What makes you think I'd stick my neck out for Laszlo?
第一  你赌十万法O他能逃掉
Because, one, you bet 10,000 francs he'd escape.
第二  你有那些过境信  不必否认了
Two, you've got the letters of transit. Don't bother to deny it.
你可能会那样做 只为了你不喜欢史查沙的长相
And you might do it simply because you don't like Strasser's looks.
事实上  我也不喜欢
As a matter of fact, I don't either.
极佳的理由
They're all excellent reasons.
别太依赖我的友谊  瑞克
Don't count too much on my friendship.
在这件事上  我无能为力 况且我可能输十万法O
In this matter I' m powerless. Besides, I might lose the 10,000 francs.
你不算很奸滑  不过很有效 我明白你的意思
You're not very subtle, but you are effective. I get the point.
对  我有那些信
Yes, I have the letters.
但是我打算自己用
But I intend using them myself.
我要搭今晚最后的班机 离开卡萨布兰卡
I'm leaving Casablanca on tonight's plane. The last plane.
我要带一位朋友一道走 一位你会赞赏的朋友
And I' m taking a friend with me. One you'll appreciate.
什么朋友?  伊莎林
- What friend? - Ilsa Lund.
可以打消你认为 我会帮忙拉斯路逃走的想法吧
That ought to put your mind to rest about my helping Laszlo escape.
我最不愿意在美国看到的人
The last man I want to see in America.
你来这里不是为了告诉我这些 你有过境信
You didn't come here to tell me this. You have the letters of transit.
你可以填上你和她的名字 爱什么时候走都可以
You can fill in your name and hers and leave anytime you please.
为什么你仍然对 拉斯路的境遇感兴趣
Why are you still interested in what happens to Laszlo?
我没有  不过我对伊莎和我 以后的境遇感兴趣
I'm not. But I am interested in what happens to llsa and me.
我们有合法权利离开是不是
We have a legal right to go, that's true...
不过即使有合法的权利 曾经也有人被留在卡萨布兰卡
...but people have been held in Casablanca in spite of their legal rights.
为什么你认为我们会留置你 伊莎是拉斯路的妻子
- What makes you think we want to hold you? - Ilsa is Laszlo 's wife.
她大概知道一些 史查沙想知道的事
She probably knows things that Strasser would like to know.
路易  我跟你来一项协议
Louis, I' II make a deal with you.
不用这项你加给他的小罪名 而找些真正的大罪名
Instead of this petty charge against him, you could get something big...
可叫他待在集中营好几年的
...something that would chuck him in a concentration camp for years...
可是大功一件  对不?  不错
- Be quite a feather in your cap, wouldn't it? - Certainly.
德国和维琪政府会很感激
Germany... Vichy would be very grateful.
那就释放他
Then release him.
飞机起飞前半小时你到我的店
You be at my place a half -hour before the plane leaves.
我安排拉斯路来拿过境信
I'll have Laszlo come there to pick up the letters...
那便给你犯罪的证据以逮捕他
...and that'll give you grounds to make the arrest.
你逮到他  而我们逃掉了
You get him, and we get away.
对德国人来说 后者只会带来轻度的苦恼
To the Germans, that last will be just a minor annoyance.
这交易我还有些地方不太明白
There's still something about this I don't quite understand.
林小姐  她非常美丽  不错
Miss Lund, she is very beautiful, yes...
可是你从不对任何女人感兴趣
...but you were never interested in any woman.
她不只是任何女人 我明白了
- She isn't just any woman. - I see.
我怎么知道你会守信
How do I know you'll keep your end of the bargain?
我马上在探访室 跟拉斯路安排好
I'll make the arrangements now with Laszlo in the visitor's pen.
瑞克  我将会怀念你
I'm gonna miss you.
很明显你是在卡萨布兰卡 唯一比我更无顾忌的人
You're the only one in Casablanca who has less scruples than I.
谢谢
Oh, thanks.
去吧  瑞克
Go ahead, Ricky.
你放他走后调走你的看门狗
Call off your watchdogs when you let him go.
我不要他今天下午在附近
I don't want them around this afternoon.
我不能冒险  路易  即使跟你
I'm taking no chances, Louis, not even with you.
我们要不要签一份文件 还是握手就够了
Should we draw up papers, or is a handshake good enough?
当然是不够  不过我很忙 只好这样了
Certainly not good enough. But since I' m in a hurry, it'll have to do.
离开卡萨布兰卡去美国 你是幸运的人
To get out of Casablanca and go to America... You're a lucky man.
我跟山姆的协定一直是 他得到利润的百分之二十五
My agreement with Sam is that he gets 25 percent of the profits.
那仍然维持
That still goes.
我凑巧知道是百分之十 不过他值百分之二十五
I happen to know he gets 10 percent. But he's won'th 25.
阿都  卡尔和沙克要留在店里 不然我不卖
Abdul, Carl and Sascha, they stay with the place or I don't sell.
当然 没有他们就不是瑞克咖啡馆
Of course. Rick's wouldn't be Rick's without them.
再会
Well, so long.
别忘了 你欠咖啡馆一百箱美国烟
Don't forget you owe Rick's 100 can'tons of American cigarettes.
我会记得付给自己
I shall remember to pay it to myself.
“关闭，警察首长命令”
你迟到了  我接到通知拉斯路刚离开饭店
- You're late. - I was informed when Laszlo left the hotel...
我会来得及的
...so I knew I' d be on time.
我想我说过 把你的看门狗绑起来
- I asked you to tie up your watchdogs.
不会有人跟踪他来这里
- He won't be followed here.
你知道没有你 这地方会完全不一样
This place will never be the same without you.
我知道你的意思 可是我已经跟法拉利说好
I know what you mean. But I' ve spoken to Ferrari.
你在轮盘上仍然可以赢
You'll still win at roulette.
一切都准备好了吗?  信就在这
- Is everything ready? - I have the letters right here.
告诉我 我们搜查时藏在那里?
When we searched the place, where were they?
山姆的钢琴
Sam's piano.
我活该  没有音乐细胞
Serves me right for not being musical.
他们来了
Here they are.
你最好到我办公室等
You better wait in my office.
拿去
理查  维多以为我跟他一起走  你没有告诉他吗?
Victor thinks I' m leaving with him. Havert you told him?
不  还没有 可是没有关系对不对?
- Not yet. - But you were able to arrange everything?
你已经安排好一切 一切都很好
Everything is quite all right.
我们在机场告诉他  越少时间去想  对大家越好过
We'll tell him at the airport. The less time to think, the easier.
请相信我
Please trust me.
是  我会
Yes, I will.
宾勒先生 我不知道如何感谢你
- I don't know how to thank you.
省省吧  我们还有很多事要做
- Save it. We've still lots of things to do.
我把钱带走了  宾勒先生 留着吧  在美国你会需要的
- I brought the money. - Keep it, you'll need it in America.
可是我们协定过 别管它
- But we made a deal. - Never mind that.
你在里斯本不会有麻烦吧?  不会  一切都安排好了
- You won't have any trouble in Lisbon? - No. It 's all arranged.
很好  信就在这里  从没用过
Good. I' ve got the letters here, made out in blank.
你只要补上签名就好了
All you have to do is fill in the signatures.
维多拉斯路
Victor Laszlo.
维多拉斯路  你被捕了
Victor Laszlo, you're under arrest.
罪名是  快递员谋杀案的帮凶
The charge of accessory to the murder of the couriers from...
这些信是从他们身上偷的
...whom the letters were stolen.
对 你对我的朋友瑞克感到意外  理由很简单
You're surprised about my friend Ricky? The explanation is simple.
爱情似乎战胜德行  谢谢...
Love, it seems, has triumphed over virtue. Thank...
且慢  路易  不会有人被捕 起码不是现在
Not so fast, Louis. Nobody is going to be arrested. Not for a while yet.
你是不是疯了?
- Have you lost your mind? - I have. Sit down.
我是  到那边坐下 把枪放下  路易  我不想开枪打你
- Put that gun down. - I don't want to shoot you...
但如果你再踏一步我会的
...but I will if you take one more step.
在这情况下  我会坐下
Under the circumstances, I will sit down.
把手放在桌上 我猜你知道你在做什么
- Keep your hands on the table.
不过我怀疑你知否这代表什么
- I wonder if you realize what this means.
我知道 待会儿我们有很多时间讨论
I do. We've got time to discuss that later.
调走你的看门狗  你说的
Call off your watchdogs, you said.
同样的  你打电话到机场  让我听到你告诉他们
Just the same, call the airport and let me hear you tell them.
记得这把枪正对着你的心脏
And remember, this gun is pointed right at your heart.
那是我最不脆弱的地方
That is my least vulnerable spot.
哈罗  是机场吗?
Hello? Is that the airport?
我是雷诺队长
This is Captain Renault speaking.
有两份过境信要用来搭乘 往里斯本的班机
There'll be two letters of transit for the Lisbon plane.
绝不能阻止他们
There's to be no trouble about them.
好
Good.
哈罗?  哈罗?
Hello?
我的车  快点 是  少校
My car, quickly!
我是史查沙少校
This is Major Strasser.
马上派一队警员 到机场跟我会合
Have a squad of police meet me at the airport at once.
马上  你听到吗?
At once, do you hear?
喂  控制塔  听得到吗?
Hello, radio tower?
往里斯本的班机十分钟后起飞 东跑道
Lisbon plane taking off in 10 minutes, east runway.
能见度一又二分之一哩
Visibility, 11/2 miles.
地面薄雾的深度大约五百
Light ground fog. Depth of fog approximately 500.
上升高度不受限制  谢谢
Ceiling unlimited. Thank you.
路易  叫你的手下 随拉斯路先生去安置好行李
Have your man go with Laszlo and take care of his luggage.
当然  瑞克  一切依你
Certainly, Rick, anything you say.
拿拉斯路的行李放在飞机上
- Find Laszlo 's luggage. Put it on the plane. - Yes, sir.
是  长官 请走这边
This way, please.
如果你不介意  你填上名字 那会更正式一点
If you don't mind, fill in the names. That'll make it more official.
你什么都设想周到  对不对?
You think of everything, don't you?
名字是维多拉斯路先生太太
And the names are Mr. And Mrs. Victor Laszlo.
可是  为什么是我的名字 理查 因为你要上那架飞机
- But why my name, Richard? - Because you're getting on that plane.
我不明白  那你呢?
I don't understand. What about you?
我留在这里看着他 等飞机安全离开为止
I'm staying with him till the plane gets away.
不  理查  你怎么回事?  昨晚
No. What has happened? Last night you said...
昨晚我们说了很多
Last night we said a great many things.
你说我要为我俩考虑
You said I was to do the thinking for us.
自那时候起我想了很多 想来想去只有一个结论
I've done a lot of it since then. It adds up to one thing:
你跟维多一起上那架飞机 你是属于他的
You're getting on that plane with Victor where you belong.
你非听我说不可
Now, you've got to listen to me.
知不知道如果你留在这里 会有什么后果
Any idea what you'd have to look forward to if you stayed here?
十分之九的机会 我们两个将被关在集中营 对不对?
Chances are we'd both wind up in a concentration camp. True, Louis?
我恐怕史查沙少校会坚持要
I'm afraid Major Strasser would insist.
你这样说只是为了叫我走 我这样说是因为那是事实
- You're saying this only to make me go. - I' m saying it because it's true.
我们的心里都明白你属于维多
Inside of us we both know you belong with Victor.
你是他工作的一部分 他的精神鼓励
You're part of his work, the thing that keeps him going.
如果飞机离地  你不在上面 你会后悔的
If that plane leaves and you're not with him, you'll regret it.
或者不是今天 或者不是明天  不过很快
Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow, but soon, and for the rest of your life.
并且是后悔一辈子 那我们呢?
But what about us?
我们永远拥有巴黎
We'll always have Paris.
本来没有 你来卡萨布兰卡后我们失去了
We didn't have... We'd lost it until you came to Casablanca.
不过昨晚我们重拾回来
We got it back last night.
昨晚我说我永远不离开你  你永远不会
- When I said I would never leave you. - And you never will.
我也有工作要做
But I' ve got a job to do too.
我要去的地方你不能跟来 我要做的事你无法参与
Where I' m going, you can't follow. What I've got to do you can't be any part of.
伊莎  清高我并不在行
Ilsa, I' m no good at being noble.
不过要明白也不难
But it doesn't take much to see that the problems of three little people...
在这疯狂的世界 三个小人物就别太计较了
...don't amount to a hill of beans in this crazy world.
总有一天你会明白的
Someday you'll understand that.
而现在...
Now, now.
永志不忘
Here's looking at you, kid.
一切都就绪  除了一件事
- Everything is in order. - All except one thing.
在你离开前有些事你应该知道
There's something you should know.
宾勒先生 你不要求你解释什么
I don't ask you to explain anything.
我打算要 因为往后可能会影响到你
I'm going to anyway. It may make a difference to you later on.
你说你知道伊莎和我的事 对
You said you knew about llsa and me.
你不知道昨晚你进来时 她正在我的店里
You didn't know she was at my place last night when you were.
她来是为了过境信  对不?  伊莎
She came there for the letters of transit. Isn't that true, llsa?
对
Yes.
可是都没有效
She tried everything to get them. Nothing worked.
她尽全力让我相信她仍爱着我
She did her best to convince me that she was still in love with me.
那在很久以前就结束了
But that was all over long ago.
为了你的缘故  她假装不是  我让她继续假装下去
For your sake, she pretended it wasrt, and I let her pretend.
我明白
I understand.
拿去 谢谢
- Here it is. - Thanks.
我很感激
I appreciate it.
欢迎你回到战线上
Welcome back to the fight.
这一次我知道我们这边会赢
This time I know our side will win.
你准备好了吗?  伊莎
Are you ready, llsa?
对  我准备好了
Yes, I' m ready.
再见  瑞克
Goodbye, Rick.
上帝祝福你
God bless you.
最好赶快不然你会搭不上飞机
You better hurry. You'll miss that plane.
我是对的 你是个感情用事的人
I was right. You are a sentimentalist.
留在原地 我不知你在说什么?
Stay where you are. I don't know what you're talking about.
你刚才为拉斯路做的事
What you just did for Laszlo.
你为了叫伊莎跟他走 编的童话故事
That fairy tale you invented to send llsa away with him.
我对女人略知一二  朋友
I know a little about women, my friend. She went.
她走了  不过她知道你说谎
But she knew you were lying.
不管如何感谢你帮我忙
Anyway, thanks for helping me out.
我假定你知道我们都将不好过 特别是你
I suppose you know this isn't going to be pleasant for either of us.
当然我必须逮捕你 飞机一走马上可以  路易
- I' II have to arrest you, of course. - As soon as the plane goes, Louis.
那通电话是什么意思?  维多拉斯路在那架飞机上
- What was the meaning of that phone call? - Victor Laszlo is on that plane.
你为何站在这?  你为何不阻止他
Why do you stand here? Why don't you stop him?
问瑞克先生
Ask Monsieur Rick.
离开那电话 我劝你不要干涉
- Get away from that phone. - I advise you not to interfere.
我愿意开枪打雷诺队长 也会愿意打你
I was willing to shoot Captain Renault, and I' m willing to shoot you.
哈罗 把电话放下
- Hello! - Put that phone down.
替我接控制塔 放下!
- Get me the radio tower. - Put it down!
史查沙少校被射杀
Major Strasser has been shot.
围捕可疑的嫌犯 是  队长
Round up the usual suspects.
(维琪矿泉水)
瑞克  你不只是感情用事 你已变成爱国份子了
Well, Rick, you're not only a sentimentalist, but you've become a patriot.
似乎现在是开始的好时机
Maybe, but it seemed like a good time to start.
我想你是对的
I think perhaps you're right.
你在卡萨布兰卡消失一段时间 可能是个好主意
It might be a good idea for you to disappear from Casablanca for a while.
在巴撒市那边有自由法国驻军
There's a Free French garrison over at Brazzaville.
我可以帮你安排通行  我的过境信
- I could be induced to arrange a passage. - My letter of transit?
我大可去旅行
I could use a trip.
那不影响我们的赌注 你仍然欠我十万法O
But it doesn't change our bet. You still owe me 10,000 francs.
那十万法O应该够我们的开销
That 10,000 francs should pay our expenses.
我们的开销?
"Our" expenses?
路易 我想这是美好友谊的开始
Louis, I think this is the beginning of a beautiful friendship.